<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Free trade, or, The meanes to make trade florish. Wherein, the causes of the decay of trade in this kingdome are discouered and the remedies also to remooue the same are represented.</title>
            <author>Misselden, Edward, fl. 1608-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14801</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">28146521</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177945</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248550683</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 17987</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S100059</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1281:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Free trade, or, The meanes to make trade florish. Wherein, the causes of the decay of trade in this kingdome are discouered and the remedies also to remooue the same are represented.</title>
                  <author>Misselden, Edward, fl. 1608-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition with some addition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[16], 134, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt for Simon Waterson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Tariff --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Free trade --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177945:1"/>
            <p>FREE TRADE. <hi>OR,</hi> THE MEANES TO MAKE TRADE FLORISH.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN, The Causes of the Decay of <hi>Trade</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> are discouered: And the Remedies also to remooue the same, are represented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The second Edition with some Addition.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROPERTIVS.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Nauita de ventis, de tauris narrat arator:</p>
               <p>Enumerat miles vulnera pastor oues.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt,</hi> for <hi>Simon Waterson,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard at the Signe of the Crowne. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177945:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177945:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR HIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES</hi> is no lesse <hi>Happy</hi> to bee the <hi>SONNE</hi> of so great a <hi>KING,</hi> then to be the <hi>Heire apparent</hi> of so many <hi>Kingdomes.</hi> In
<pb facs="tcp:177945:3"/> the <hi>one,</hi> rare endowments of <hi>Maiesty</hi> and <hi>Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity,</hi> are <hi>Yours</hi> by <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration:</hi> In the <hi>other,</hi> a <hi>Royall Monarchy by inheritance and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> doth fit <hi>You</hi> for the <hi>other,</hi> and <hi>Your Royall FATHERS footsteps</hi> for them <hi>both.</hi> In <hi>those</hi> are <hi>Peerelesse prints: You</hi> cannot cast <hi>Your Eie,</hi> but they are present to <hi>You,</hi> and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented in <hi>You. You</hi> see in <hi>HIS Religion, Piety:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177945:3"/> in <hi>HIS Sacred Person, Tranquility:</hi> in <hi>HIS Gouernment, Policy.</hi> In euery <hi>one</hi> of these, <hi>all</hi> these: and <hi>all</hi> in <hi>You.</hi> In that last, <hi>HIS Maiesty</hi> hath carried a quick <hi>Eie,</hi> ouer the <hi>Commerce</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome:</hi> because it hath relation both to the <hi>Reuenue of the Crowne,</hi> and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> of all <hi>HIS Kingdomes.</hi> It is said in <hi>Ezechiels Vision,</hi> that <hi>One wheele ran within
<pb facs="tcp:177945:4"/> the other,</hi> which hath an <hi>Emphasis</hi> in that tongue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and surely matters of <hi>STATE</hi> and of <hi>TRADE,</hi> are involued and wrapt vp together. Which latter, because it is at this time in agitation, and there are, notwithout cause, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Quaere's</hi> about the <hi>Causes</hi> of the generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay thereof; hath caused me to put my selfe on this <hi>Enquiry,</hi> to <hi>philosophize</hi> if I could, in these <hi>Causes</hi> and <hi>Remedies.</hi> Not
<pb facs="tcp:177945:4"/> that I would seeme with <hi>Phormio,</hi> to reade a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture to <hi>Hannibal:</hi> No, I haue only <hi>mustered</hi> and <hi>marshalled</hi> these <hi>men</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>Rancks</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> it is <hi>Yours</hi> to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. Great <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> suffered a meane musition to say vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Absit, vt haec tu me melius scias.</hi> But for my part, I dare not in any thing, put <hi>such</hi> an <hi>absit,</hi> to a <hi>PRINCE so absolute.</hi> Euery thing mooues it selfe
<pb facs="tcp:177945:5"/> to its <hi>Center.</hi> These little lucubrations present them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to your <hi>HIGHNES,</hi> as vnto their proper <hi>Orb.</hi> For as they <hi>looke</hi> vp to the <hi>KING,</hi> or as they <hi>looke downe</hi> to the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> In both they looke on <hi>YOV,</hi> with a double aspect. <hi>YOV</hi> are the <hi>Ioy</hi> of the <hi>KING,</hi> the <hi>Hope</hi> of all these <hi>Kingdomes.</hi> The <hi>Only Sonne YOV</hi> are, of the <hi>Only KING:</hi> An hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py<note n="*" place="margin">Ex <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> prospexit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidit, quasi portò-vidit.</note>
               <hi>SEER,</hi> of a blessed <hi>SIRE:</hi> A <hi>Princely
<pb facs="tcp:177945:5"/> CONSVL,</hi> of <hi>the Priuy Councel: A watchman, A worthy,</hi> of <hi>DAVID</hi> and of <hi>IACOB.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These Meditations of <hi>mine,</hi> are very <hi>meane:</hi> an vnfit obiect for a <hi>Princes</hi> sight: vnlesse as <hi>YOV</hi> are <hi>a God on Earth;</hi> in this also <hi>YOV</hi> represent <hi>the GOD of Heauen;</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in your <hi>Princely</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and patience, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Cause is great, your Wisedom's deep, and my <hi>Lord the KING</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177945:6"/> is as an <hi>Angell of GOD. YOV</hi> are <hi>HIS, HE</hi> is<note n="*" place="margin">Not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> too.</note>
               <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and <hi>CHRIST</hi> is <hi>GODS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh GOD,</hi> be thou still the <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>CHRIST,</hi> of this <hi>CHRIST</hi> Our <hi>KING: Euangelize</hi> vnto this <hi>Angel:</hi> double the Spirit of Our <hi>ELIAH,</hi> on Our <hi>ELISHA:</hi> that <hi>HE</hi> may flourish like our <hi>Palme Tree,</hi> and grow vp like our <hi>Cedar</hi> of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Libanon</hi> per Litterarum Metathesm, <hi>Albion.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Albion.</hi> Giue thy <hi>Iudgements</hi> to the <hi>KING,</hi> and thy <hi>Iustice</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177945:6"/> to the <hi>KINGS SONNE:</hi> And let all the <hi>People</hi> offer these sweete <hi>Odours</hi> to <hi>Thee</hi> the <hi>God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> and pray for the life of the <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>HIS SONNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prayeth, for HIS Maiestie, And your Highnesse,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>EDW. MISSELDEN,</hi> Merchant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my House at</hi> Hackney <hi>on</hi> Whatson Eue,
<date>
                     <hi>the 8 of</hi> Iune <hi>In the yeare of</hi> Grace, <hi>M.DC.XXII. And of the KING of</hi> Peace, <hi>XX.LV.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177945:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, <hi>Si ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum me dixeris, omnia dixeris.</hi> I should haue <hi>premised</hi> my prayer for thy <hi>patience,</hi> to cast thine Eie on such a worthlesse worke: but thou hast <hi>preuented</hi> me with thy kinde <hi>acceptance;</hi> euen of the whole <hi>Impression,</hi> within a very little <hi>Interstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of time. So that now thou hast turned my <hi>petition,</hi> into a thankefull <hi>retribution:</hi> for which accept I pray thee, this second <hi>Edition,</hi> with some small <hi>addition,</hi> as a <hi>Symbolum</hi> of my seruice to the publique.</p>
            <p>That I haue proposed any thing to my selfe, then the <hi>Commō-good;</hi> I hope I shall neede no <hi>Apologie:</hi> to haue expected to please all men; I might rather haue wish't it,
<pb facs="tcp:177945:7"/> then imagined any <hi>possibility.</hi> But if there should be any offence, it shall be <hi>Acceptum</hi> not <hi>Datum,</hi> as I shall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> make manifest, if there be any cause of <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some men aske me, <hi>Quorsum haec Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctura?</hi> Wherefore all this cost and wast of learning &amp; languages, in the troddē way of <hi>Trade?</hi> And tell me that I seem to <hi>plow</hi> with others <hi>Heyfers,</hi> as if it were not cōtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to a <hi>Merchant,</hi> to be acquainted with the <hi>Muses.</hi> Surely it is with many, the price of these paines: that <hi>litterae</hi> and <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terati non habent jnimicum praeter ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantem.</hi> But it is thy humanity rather to ascribe <hi>learning</hi> to the <hi>vnlearned:</hi> I feare alas, in mine vnlearned lines, the learned finde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>pro thesauro Carbones.</hi> If there were any, I should pray thee to accept it, for illustration of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not affectation in the Author: and to thinke that learning and languages are an Appendix not vnnecessary to the facultie of a Merchant. And for supply of other mens learning, to <hi>succenturiat</hi> my wants, I needed it, I confesse, but tooke it not.</p>
            <p>Others tell me, that I seeme to detract something from the Netherlands Nation, and Natiue Commodities of those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.
<pb facs="tcp:177945:8"/> But for my part, there are many in that Nation, that can report of my loue to either. For the former, as things now stand; J wish wee were not <hi>Loosers,</hi> so we had not this <hi>Leaue:</hi> yet that which is spoken of the <hi>Part,</hi> must not alwaies be vnderstood of the <hi>Whole.</hi> And as I must giue them their due, that they are a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ingenious</hi> Nation; so I wish those whom it concerneth, would shew themselues <hi>ingenuous</hi> also, and deale with vs, as <hi>freely</hi> as <hi>fairely,</hi> in the <hi>Close</hi> of that great <hi>East-India Cause.</hi> And for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the learned know, that when <hi>Nothing</hi> and <hi>All things</hi> are opposed, what the sense must be: and that alwaies <hi>In dubijs benigniora sunt praeserenda.</hi> Yet least I seem to lacke a <hi>Voucher</hi> for that J said, let them heare <hi>SCALIGER</hi> thus writing to their famous <hi>DOVSA,</hi> on the same sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect:
<q>
                  <l>Ignorata ruae, referam miracula terrae,</l>
                  <l>DOVSA peregrinis non habitura fidem.</l>
                  <l>Omnia lanicium hîc lassat textrina Minerua:</l>
                  <l>Lanigeros tamen hinc scimus abeste greges.</l>
                  <l>Non capiunt operas fabriles oppida vestra:</l>
                  <l>Nulla fabris tamē haec ligna ministrat humus.</l>
                  <l>Horrea triticeae rumpunt hîc frugis acerbi:</l>
                  <l>Pascuus hîc tamen est, non Cerealis age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177945:8"/>
                  <l>Hîc numerosa meri stipantur dolia Cellis:</l>
                  <l>Quae vineta colat nulla putator habet.</l>
                  <l>Hic nulla aut cerrè seges est rarissima Lini:</l>
                  <l>Linifici tamen est Copia major vbi?</l>
                  <l>Hic medijs habitamus aquis: quis credere possit?</l>
                  <l>Et tamen hic nullae, DOVSA, bibuntur aquae.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Curteous Reader, at last I'le let thee rest: And if I haue longer mine, thou shalt haue thine. And shall be alwayes for thy sake,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>In Vtrunque paratus,</hi> E. M.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex Bibliopolae officinâ haec paucula rapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> apponebam,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>6. Iulij. 1622.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:177945:9"/>
            <p>A <hi>view</hi> of the <hi>Trade</hi> of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deformed,</hi> in the
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Causes.</hi> in
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Matter.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Natural.</hi> CAP. 1.</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Artificial</hi> CAP. 2.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Forme.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Gouerned.</hi> CAP. 3.</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Vngouerned.</hi> CAP. 4.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Effects,</hi> which extend,
<list>
                              <item>To the <hi>King.</hi> CAP. 5</item>
                              <item>To the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> CAP. 6.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reformed,</hi> in the <hi>Remedies</hi> being applied to all the parts of this distribution in their Order. CAP. 7.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177945:9"/>
            <head>CAP. I. The Causes of the want <hi>of Money in England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hauing pleased <hi>God</hi> to giue mee my <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in this <hi>Good Land,</hi> and vnder the <hi>Reigne</hi> of so <hi>Great a</hi> KING; whose <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> whose <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> whose rare endowments of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Literature, absit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis adulatio,</hi> doe <hi>Lend</hi> to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177945:10"/>
               <hi>Christian</hi> and <hi>Pagan</hi> world such a <hi>Glorious Lustre,</hi> as that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Great Lights</hi> in the <hi>Spheares</hi> thereof do seeme <hi>Eclipsed:</hi> I could not but thinke it my bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in all humble acknowledgement to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> and deuoted ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to so <hi>Mighty</hi> a KING, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to expresse the same, in some <hi>Publique Seruice</hi> for the <hi>Publique good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rather for that there seemes to bee a necessity imposed vpon all men, as much as they can, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this duty; according to that generall precept,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Feare God, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King:</hi> As if a man could not <hi>Feare God,</hi> vnlesse hee <hi>Honour the King:</hi> nor <hi>Honour the King,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Feare of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And no maruell; when <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe setteth these duties in the <hi>Frontispice</hi> or top of both the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the <hi>Decalogue:</hi> The one <hi>Explicit</hi> in the first Table, <hi>Thou
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177945:10"/> shalt loue the Lord thy God:</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Implicit</hi> in the second Table, <hi>Thou shalt honour the King:</hi> as if here were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>another Law:</hi> yea the <hi>Whole Law</hi> comprised in these <hi>Two:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and these <hi>Two</hi> termed the <hi>Great Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to giue a deepe <hi>Impression</hi> and a liuely <hi>Expression</hi> of so great a duty.</p>
            <p>Yea, he doth honour <hi>Kings</hi> with his owne <hi>Title,</hi> as if he would <hi>Part</hi> with, and <hi>Impart</hi> to them, some of his owne <hi>Honour. I haue sayd ye are Gods:</hi> to which that of the <hi>Poet</hi> may seeme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to haue an elegant allusion,<note place="margin">In vita Virg.</note>
               <hi>Diuisum imperium cum Ioue Caesar habet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is it I confesse that hath <hi>Raised</hi> &amp; <hi>Rowsed</hi> mine <hi>Affections,</hi> to seeke out a <hi>Subiect,</hi> wherein I might set my selfe a taske, and as it is in the <hi>Prouerbe,</hi> might <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to performe some acceptable seruice, to so <hi>Great a King,</hi> &amp; so <hi>Good a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177945:11"/>
            <p>But what need I <hi>Seeke</hi> that which <hi>Seeketh</hi> all men? For what is at this time more enquired after then the <hi>Causes</hi> of the <hi>Decay of Trade?</hi> And what can be more fit for my <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> then that wherein I haue had <hi>Education?</hi> And what hath more relation to matters of <hi>State,</hi> then <hi>Commerce</hi> of Merchants? For when <hi>Trade flourisheth, the Kings Reuenue is augmented, Lands and Rents improoued, Nauigation is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, the poore employed.</hi> But if <hi>Trade</hi> decay, <hi>All these</hi> decline with it. Neuerthelesse when I looke vpon the <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>Great body politique</hi> of this <hi>Weale publike,</hi> and therein consider the <hi>High wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of HIS <hi>sacred Maiesty,</hi> as the <hi>intellectual part</hi> of this <hi>Microcosme,</hi> or <hi>alter orbis</hi> as <hi>Caesar</hi> calles it: the <hi>Prudence</hi> &amp; <hi>Prouidence</hi> of HIS <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> as the <hi>Eyes</hi> thereof; the great decay of <hi>Trade,</hi> the <hi>Nerues</hi> thereof: together with the <hi>Parliamentation</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177945:11"/> and <hi>Consultation</hi> of all the <hi>Parts</hi> together about these <hi>Causes</hi> and <hi>Remedies:</hi> I feare I shall seeme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to light a Candle in the Sunne, to offer my seruice in that, about which the choicest wits of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> are now in consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>But hauing had experience of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> gracious interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of small seruices of his subiects employed for the publique: though <hi>Others</hi> much more sufficient are <hi>Sent before,</hi> yet could I not but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulate with my selfe, what if I also <hi>Runne after,</hi> and cast in my <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, into this great <hi>Treasury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore if herein, any obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mine, either <hi>Forrein or Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stique,</hi> may administer any thing worthy the information of that <hi>Great common</hi> and yet <hi>not common Sense,</hi> I shall esteeme my part most happily acted, to haue imployed my <hi>Priuate paines</hi> for the <hi>Publique
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177945:12"/> good.</hi> The rather, for that, as there are many <hi>Causes discussed</hi> and <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed</hi> of at this time, of the <hi>decay of Trade;</hi> so also are there many <hi>Remedies:</hi> wherein if either the <hi>Causes</hi> be mistaken, or the <hi>Remedies</hi> ill applyed; the present sicknesse of the <hi>Trade,</hi> may be brought from a disease in <hi>Fieri,</hi> to an <hi>Habituated</hi> and in <hi>Facto,</hi> as the <hi>phisitians Schoole</hi> hath it.</p>
            <p>To find out the <hi>Causes</hi> of things, is a worke of <hi>Philosophy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Felix qui potuit rerum cognos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere causas. Virg.</note> and much <hi>Felicity,</hi> to finde out a fit <hi>Remedy,</hi> is of high <hi>Eminency:</hi> But to apply the <hi>Remedy,</hi> is a matter of <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Policy.</hi> And this leadeth mee to the <hi>Method</hi> of my <hi>Discourse:</hi> which parts it selfe in twaine: <hi>viz.</hi> Into a <hi>double Quaere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> of the <hi>Deformation</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> of Trade. In the <hi>former</hi> may be considered, the <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> and <hi>Effects</hi> thereof. In the <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> of Trade. The <hi>Matter</hi> of Trade, is either
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177945:12"/>
               <hi>Naturall</hi> or <hi>Artificiall.</hi> The <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral matter</hi> of <hi>Commerce</hi> is <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize:</hi> which <hi>Merchants</hi> from the end of <hi>Trade</hi> haue stiled <hi>Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> The <hi>Artificiall matter</hi> of <hi>Commerce</hi> is <hi>Mony,</hi> which hath obtained the title of <hi>Sinewes</hi> of <hi>Warre</hi> and of <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Old Iacob</hi> blessing his <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children,</hi> crost his hands, and laid his right hand on the <hi>Yonger,</hi> and his left hand on the <hi>Elder:</hi> And <hi>Money,</hi> though it be in <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> after <hi>Merchandize,</hi> yet foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is now in vse become the chiefe, I will take leaue of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, to handle it in the first place.<note place="margin">The Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate cause of the want of Money in England, is the vnder valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of his Maiesties Coyne, which hindereth the Importation, and causeth the exportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof.</note>
            </p>
            <p>First therefore for the <hi>Want</hi> of <hi>Money</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons may bee assign'd. Whereof some are <hi>Immediate,</hi> some <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi> or remote. The <hi>Immediate</hi> reasons of the want of Money, are either such as <hi>Hinder</hi> the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177945:13"/>
               <hi>Importation;</hi> or as such <hi>Cause</hi> the <hi>Exportation</hi> thereof. And <hi>Both</hi> these are occasioned by the <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-valuation</hi> of <hi>his</hi> MAIESTIES <hi>Coyne,</hi> to that of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Countries.</hi> For who will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Licence in <hi>Spaine</hi> to bring <hi>Realles</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> to sell them here at Ten in the hundred gaine, which is lesse then the <hi>Exchange</hi> from thence will yeeld;<note place="margin">Spanish Reals worth 15. in the C. in Holland.</note> when hee may haue for the same <hi>Fiue and Twenty</hi> in the hundred in <hi>Holland?</hi> Here fiue <hi>Reals</hi> of eight, which make <hi>Twenty</hi> shillings sterling, will commonly yeeld <hi>Two and Twenty</hi> shillings or thereabouts: and the same in <hi>Holland</hi> will yeeld <hi>Forty two shillings and sixe pence</hi> Flemish, which is <hi>Fine and Twenty</hi> shillings sterling. And how can wee choose but want money in <hi>England,</hi> when the <hi>Iacobus</hi> pieces are currant at so high a rate in <hi>Holland?</hi> For there they goe at <hi>Twelue</hi> Gilders <hi>eight
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177945:13"/> stiuers</hi> the piece, which is <hi>One</hi> and <hi>forty shillings</hi> and <hi>foure pence</hi> Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish, which is <hi>Foure</hi> and <hi>Twenty shillings</hi> &amp; <hi>nine pence</hi> sterling. And about this rate HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Coynes</hi> of <hi>gold</hi> &amp; <hi>siluer</hi> are there of respectiue value. For although by the <hi>Placcaets</hi> or <hi>Proclamations</hi> of those parts, the <hi>Iacobus</hi> pieces, &amp; other <hi>Species</hi> of gold and siluer, are there set at indifferent rates an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to their valuation here with vs respectiuely, which they there call <hi>Permissie gelt, Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion money:</hi> yet they haue other deuices to raise money, and draw it away at their pleasures. As either by their <hi>Banckes,</hi> when the <hi>Bancki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> will for their occasions giue a greater price for mony then the <hi>Proclamation</hi> suffereth, and then it is called <hi>Banck gelt:</hi> or else by slacke paymasters, that for their owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage in the raising of Money, will pretend not to make present
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177945:14"/> payment of their debts, vnlesse you take their Money at a higher rate, then either the <hi>Proclamation,</hi> or the <hi>Banck</hi> Money. Which being paid and receiued, produceth a third kind, which they call <hi>Current gelt.</hi> And so by the Conniuence of the Magistrate, the same goeth from man to man, and at last becommeth current at an excessiue value So they haue <hi>Permission</hi> or <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Mony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Three sorts of Mony in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: Permissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Money: Banck Money: and Current Money.</note> and <hi>Banck Money,</hi> and <hi>Current Money,</hi> and all to draw dry the <hi>Current</hi> of HIS <hi>Maiesties Coine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus the <hi>Hepatites,</hi> or Liuer veine of this <hi>Great body</hi> of ours being opened, &amp; such profusiōs of the <hi>Life bloud</hi> let out; &amp; the <hi>Liuer</hi> or fountain obstructed, &amp; weakned, which shuld succour the same; needs must this <hi>Great body languish,</hi> and at length fal into a <hi>Marasmus,</hi> or Hectike Feuer.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that there hath beene great abuse in the culling of HIS <hi>Maiesties Coyne</hi> here at home,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177945:14"/> and in melting the heauy money in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plate: And that there is a great superfluity of <hi>Plate</hi> generally in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate mens hands more then is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, and farre beyond any exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of former times, which must needs also cause scarcity of money: yet on the other side I cannot deny, but that it is better to haue the same in <hi>Plate,</hi> as a <hi>Treasure</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> then <hi>turned into Coyne,</hi> and so <hi>turned out</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> by the vnder value thereof.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Mediate</hi> or remote rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the want of money in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>The Mediate Causes of the want of money are Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stique or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine.</p>
                  <p>The Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stique is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, Excesse.</p>
               </note> are either <hi>Domestique</hi> or <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine.</hi> The <hi>Domestique</hi> are <hi>General</hi> or <hi>Special.</hi> The <hi>General remote</hi> cause of our want of money, is the <hi>great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in consuming the <hi>Commodities</hi> of <hi>Forreine Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> which proue to vs <hi>Discommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities,</hi> in hindering vs of so much <hi>Treasure,</hi> which otherwise would bee brought in, in lieu of those
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177945:15"/>
               <hi>Toyes.</hi> For now a dayes most men liue aboue their callings, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miscuously step forth <hi>Vice versâ,</hi> into one anothers <hi>Rankes.</hi> The <hi>Countrey mans</hi> Eie is vpon the <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hesiod.</note> the <hi>Citizens</hi> vpon the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</hi> the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> vpon the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman.</hi> And by this meanes wee draw <hi>Vnto vs,</hi> and consume <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs,</hi> that great abundance of the <hi>Wines of Spaine,</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> of the <hi>Rhene,</hi> of the <hi>Leuant,</hi> and of the <hi>Ilands:</hi> the <hi>Raisins</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Corints</hi> of the <hi>Leuant,</hi> the <hi>Lawnes</hi> and <hi>Cambricks</hi> of <hi>Hannault</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the <hi>Silkes</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Sugers</hi> &amp; <hi>Tobacco</hi> of the <hi>West Indies,</hi> the <hi>Spices</hi> of the <hi>East-Indies:</hi> All which are of no necessity vnto vs, &amp; yet are <hi>bought</hi> with ready money, which otherwise would bee <hi>brought</hi> ouer in treasure if these were not. A <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is like vnto a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> or Master whereof ought to sell more then he buyeth,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177945:15"/> according to old <hi>Cato's</hi> counsell, <hi>Patrem familias vendacem non ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem esse oportet.</hi> Otherwise his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi> being greater then his <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hesiod.</note> hee must needs come behind hand. Euen so a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> that excessiuely spendeth the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine</hi> Commodities deere, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth the <hi>Natiue</hi> fewer and cheape, shall enrich other <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> but begger it selfe. Where on the contrary, if it vented fewer of the <hi>Forreigne,</hi> and more of the <hi>Natiue,</hi> the residue must needes returne in treasure.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Speciall remote cause</hi> of our want of Money,<note place="margin">The domestike cause in speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, is the want of the <hi>East-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Stocke</hi> in this <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
               </note> is the great want of our <hi>East-India Stocke</hi> heere at home. Which is a matter of very great consequence, and causeth the <hi>Body</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> to bee wounded sore, through the <hi>Sides</hi> of many particular members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For the <hi>Stocke</hi> of the <hi>East-India Company,</hi> being of great value, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177945:16"/> collected and contracted from all the other particular <hi>Trades</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> and a great part thereof hauing bin <hi>Embargued</hi> and <hi>Detained</hi> now for more, then fiue yeeres last past; and that not by a <hi>Profest Enemy,</hi> against whom wee might haue bin <hi>warn'd</hi> and <hi>Arm'd,</hi> but by a <hi>Friend,</hi> a <hi>Neighbour,</hi> a <hi>Next Neighbor,</hi> one obliged to our KING and <hi>Nation</hi> more then to all the Kings on earth: this losse I say, is not onely thus vnkind, but is the more intollerable, in that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth hath lost the vse and employment of the <hi>Stocke</hi> it selfe, and all the encrease of <hi>Trade</hi> which the same might haue produced, in the seuerall <hi>Trades</hi> of the <hi>Subiects,</hi> whereby abundance of <hi>Treasure</hi> might haue beene brought into this land in all this time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Crinitus &amp; Volater.</note>It is sayd of <hi>Belisarius</hi> that great and famous <hi>Commander</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> that euen <hi>Rome</hi> it selfe owed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177945:16"/> to him twice her life: and yet at last was so vnkind to <hi>Belisarius</hi> as to put out both his eyes, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him to beg in a little Cottage built without the gates, where hee often repeated this sentence to those that passed by, <hi>Date obolum Belisario, quem inuidia, non culpa caecauit.</hi> And certainely our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may challenge as much or more of these <hi>Vnkind Friends,</hi> then <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisarius</hi> euer did or could of <hi>Rome:</hi> and they shew themselues no lesse vnkinde, to depriue vs of the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of this <hi>Trade</hi> of ours, and suffer this <hi>Nation</hi> to vse so much importunity for their owne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homer</hi> reports of <hi>Patroclus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. Iliad.</note> that he would needs put on <hi>Achilles ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,</hi> and ride on <hi>Achilles horse,</hi> but <hi>Achilles speare</hi> he durst not touch, and thereby was knowne to <hi>Hector,</hi> with whom he fought, not to be <hi>Achilles,</hi> and so lost his life. These friends of ours haue some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177945:17"/>
               <hi>Put on,</hi> sometimes <hi>Put off,</hi> I had almost said, <hi>Put out the Kings Colours:</hi> They haue sayled in HIS subiects <hi>Shippes,</hi> but that <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stam fidei</hi> they haue not <hi>Vsed</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused</hi> rather; whereby they haue beene <hi>Discouered</hi> to the <hi>Indians,</hi> not to be the <hi>Subiects</hi> of the <hi>Faith's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Church-man. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</note> as sometimes they would haue <hi>faigned,</hi> though to an euill purpose.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanes</hi> were wont to weepe, at the sight of <hi>Caesars bloud</hi> kept in an <hi>Handkercher.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Caes. &amp; Brut.</note>
               <hi>Caesars sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects bloud</hi> is kept, not in <hi>Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes</hi> but in <hi>Sheetes,</hi> written <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> and <hi>without,</hi> the <hi>Memory</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of maketh the people <hi>mourne.</hi> The <hi>cry</hi> thereof is <hi>gone vp:</hi> the <hi>King</hi> will remember it, the <hi>King of Kings</hi> will auenge it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Euseb.</note>
               <hi>Constantinus</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> the father of <hi>Constantius,</hi> was wont often to protest, that he made more account of one <hi>Christian</hi> then of <hi>all</hi> his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177945:17"/>
               <hi>Coffers</hi> filled with <hi>Treasure.</hi> And the Comfort of this <hi>Nation</hi> is, to be the <hi>Subiects</hi> of such a <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> who as <hi>Constantly</hi> as euer did <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> hath againe and againe profest,<note place="margin">In diuers Orations and Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>
               <hi>Not to account himselfe more rich or happy, then in the prosperity of his Subiects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of the <hi>Domestique Remote causes</hi> of the want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in <hi>England:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Forreine causes of the want of money are the warres of Christians amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them by Pyrats.</note> the <hi>Forreine causes</hi> follow. Which are either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the <hi>Warres in Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> or the <hi>Trades out of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The Warres in Christendome</hi> are <hi>Forreine remote causes</hi> of the want of money, either by <hi>Causing</hi> the <hi>Exportation,</hi> as the <hi>Warres of Christians:</hi> or <hi>Hindering</hi> the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation</hi> thereof, as the <hi>Warres</hi> of <hi>Pyrates.</hi> I will take the <hi>Warres</hi> of <hi>Germany</hi> for an vrgent instance of the former: which haue raysed the <hi>Riecks daller</hi> from <hi>Two</hi> Markes <hi>Lubish,</hi> to <hi>Twenty</hi> Markes <hi>Lubish,</hi> in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177945:18"/> many places of <hi>Germany:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by abundance of Mony is drawne vnto the <hi>Mintes</hi> of <hi>those</hi> Countries, from all the other <hi>Mines</hi> and parts of <hi>Christendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the latter, I will instance the <hi>Warres</hi> of the <hi>Pirats</hi> of <hi>Argier</hi> and <hi>Tunis,</hi> which hath robbed this Common-wealth of an infinite va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue: the <hi>Cruelty</hi> whereof many feele with <hi>griefe,</hi> others heare with <hi>pitty,</hi> but the <hi>grieuance</hi> remaines. Needes must <hi>Christendome,</hi> and in it <hi>England,</hi> feele the want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, when either it is violently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted by <hi>Turkish Pirats,</hi> the Enemies of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man;</hi> or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments surprised, as <hi>Men, Ships,</hi> and <hi>Merchandize,</hi> which are the <hi>Chanels</hi> to conuey it to vs. An <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenish policy</hi> it is, or <hi>Hellish</hi> rather, put vpon the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>People of Christendome</hi> by the <hi>Grand Sieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Turkish policy.</note> to hold with them an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forme of <hi>Amity,</hi> and in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177945:18"/> meane time by his vassalls, vse a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and couert <hi>Hostility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other <hi>Forreine remote causes</hi> of the want of Money,<note place="margin">Or the trades maintained out of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome with ready money.</note> are the <hi>Trades</hi> maintained out of <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> to <hi>Turkey, Persia,</hi> and the <hi>East-Indies.</hi> Which trades are maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the most part with ready Money, yet in a different manner from the Trades of <hi>Christendome</hi> within it selfe. For although the trades within <hi>Christendome</hi> are driuen with ready Monies, yet those Monies are still <hi>Contained</hi> and <hi>Continued</hi> within the <hi>Bounds</hi> of <hi>Christendome.</hi> There is indeede a <hi>Fluxus</hi> and <hi>refluxus,</hi> a <hi>Flood</hi> and <hi>Ebbe</hi> of the monies of <hi>Christendome</hi> traded within it selfe: for sometimes there is more in one part of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome,</hi> sometimes there is lesse in another, as one Countrey wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and another aboundeth: It commeth and goeth, and whirleth about the <hi>Circle</hi> of <hi>Christendome,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177945:19"/> but is still contained within the <hi>Compasse</hi> thereof. But the money that is traded out of <hi>Christendome</hi> into the parts aforesaid, is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally issued out and neuer returneth againe. It is true, those trades tend to an admirable encrease of the stocke of <hi>Christendome</hi> in wares: which if they were purchased with the wares of <hi>Christendome,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true nature of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,</hi> the benefit were farre more excellent.<note place="margin">Benvenu t Strac. de merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pars. <hi>1.</hi> Calepiu.</note> For <hi>Commercium is qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si Commutatio mercium,</hi> a change of wares for wares, not money for wares. And it is <hi>Libera commeandi facultas, ab ijs qui merces vltro ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troque conuehunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>Christendome</hi> were like to that of<note n="*" place="margin">Aurum &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um sic apud se hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, vt à nullo pluri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uàm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ipsarum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reatur▪ quâ quis non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det quam longè infra ferrum sunt? Vtop. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Vtopia,</hi> where gold and siluer are of esse esteeme then Iron, it were a braue exchange to lose money to get wares. For the riches of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages did not consist in <hi>Re Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niariâ</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:177945:19"/> but <hi>Pecuariâ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnes veterum diuitiae in re pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuariâ consiste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant. Guich. Plin. lib. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> Whence <hi>Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niâ,</hi> as <hi>Pliny</hi> affirmeth, was so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>a Pecude, quia Pecus fuit Pecuniae fundamentum, &amp; antiquitus Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia pecudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> estigi signabatur.</hi> But when <hi>Immooueable</hi> and <hi>Immutable</hi> things came also to be in <hi>Commerce</hi> amongst men, as wel as those things which were <hi>Mooueable</hi> and fit for change, then came money in vse, as the rule and square whereby things might receiue estimation and value. Therfore the <hi>Ciuilians</hi> affirme that <hi>Numus est</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>dictus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> ff. de Contrah. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</note>
               <hi>quòd institutum sit Ciuile.</hi> According to that of <hi>Aristotle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Eth. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Numus non est à natura sed à l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge.</hi> And thence it is that <hi>Money</hi> in our tongue is deriued of <hi>Monela, quasi numi nota.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if there were a <hi>Necessity</hi> to <hi>Christendome</hi> to vse those For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine wares: or that the <hi>Meanes</hi> whereby they are to be procured, were without the losse of treasure:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177945:20"/> or lastly that the same tended to the <hi>Encrease</hi> of the <hi>Treasure</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the exchange were excellent. But first there is no such <hi>Necessity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Necessarium illud dicitur sine quo fieri non potest. Calep.</note> for that's necessary to doe a thing without which it cannot be done: And that's necessary to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> without which it cannot subsist. But thankes be to <hi>God, Christendome</hi> is richly furnished within it selfe, with all things fit for life and maintenance: whether wee respect <hi>Vitall</hi> vse, as foode and raiment: or <hi>Physicall,</hi> as vegetables and mineralls: or <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,</hi> as gold, siluer, and infinite variety of Merchandize. Nor are those wares procured without the <hi>Losse</hi> of Treasure, no nor with <hi>Lesse</hi> Treasure. For as those wares haue cost lesse in <hi>Price,</hi> since some late discoueries; so are they encreased in their <hi>Quantities,</hi> by the ample trade of all parts of <hi>Christendome</hi> thither, more then before: and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177945:20"/> then who knoweth not that a <hi>Lesse</hi> quantity <hi>Deare,</hi> and a <hi>Greater</hi> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity <hi>Cheape,</hi> is all one in respect of the value. Nor is the treasure lesse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by changing the course of Trade into those parts. For the <hi>New</hi> Trades found out, are furnished with a new supply of Money, and the <hi>Old</hi> neuerthelesse issue out as much treasure as before: by reason that the same are enlarged and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come now as great, <hi>Apart,</hi> as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they were, <hi>Together,</hi> when the <hi>New</hi> Trades, were included in the <hi>Old.</hi> So that now so much more of the Treasure of <hi>Christendome</hi> is wasted, as those <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Trades are encreased, which is to an infinite value.</p>
            <p>Nor lastly, is the <hi>Treasure</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome Encreased</hi> by those for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine trades, for the more the stocke of <hi>Christendome</hi> is thereby encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in <hi>Wares,</hi> the more it decreaseth in <hi>Treasure:</hi> which the parts of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177945:21"/>
               <hi>Christendome</hi> must needes feele by <hi>Sympathy</hi> and <hi>Compassion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this, that prudent and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth perceiued in his time, who vpon a question betwixt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi> about this matter, the Emperor vsed words to this effect: <hi>You Portugalles for a surety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">15. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Hall.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to all Christendome; for you carry nothing out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but coyne, which is hurt to all Countries.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. II.</hi> The Causes of the decay of Trade, in the Merchandize of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SVch are the <hi>Causes</hi> of the <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Trade</hi> considered in the <hi>Want of Money,</hi> the <hi>Merchandize</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>Merchandize</hi> is that naturall matter of <hi>Commerce,</hi> whereby men
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177945:21"/> busie themselues in buying and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, chopping and changing, to the encrease of <hi>Artes,</hi> and enriching of <hi>Common-wealths:</hi> according to that of the <hi>Poet,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Hesiod.</note>
               <hi>Bona lis mortalibus haec est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the end there should be a <hi>Commerce</hi> amongst men, it hath pleased <hi>God</hi> to inuite as it were, one Country to traffique with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the variety of things which the <hi>One hath,</hi> and the <hi>other hath not:</hi> that so that which is wanting to the <hi>One,</hi> might be supplied by the <hi>Other,</hi> that all might haue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</p>
            <p>Which thing the very <hi>Windes</hi> and <hi>Seas</hi> proclaime, in giuing pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage to all Nations: the <hi>Windes</hi> blowing sometimes towards one Country, sometimes toward ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that so by this <hi>Diuine Iustice,</hi> euery one might bee supplyed in things necessary for life and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177945:22"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3.4. Na. qu.</note>And this, <hi>Seneca</hi> thought to be a principall benefit of nature, <hi>Quòd &amp; vento gentis locis dissipatas mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, &amp; sua omnia in regiones ita descripsit, vt necessarium mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus esset inter ipsos Commerciū. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the benefit of the wind, hath so mixed people, dispersed in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and so distributed her gifts in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Countries, that there should be a necessity of Commerce amongst men.</hi> Which agreeth with that of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. De Repub. lib. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Est translatio rerum omnium coepta ab initio, ab eo quod est secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm naturam, cùm homines habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent plura quàm sufficerent, partim etiam pauciora negotiatione suppleri id quod naturae deest, quo commode omnibus sufficiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that we doe not goe out of the <hi>Christian world</hi> for an example hereof, let vs consider the state of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> in what a misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble case those people were, if they receiued not supply from all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177945:22"/> other <hi>Nations.</hi> They haue <hi>Nothing</hi> of their owne, and yet they seeme to possesse <hi>All things,</hi> in the <hi>Supply</hi> they receiue from <hi>All the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And surely if any <hi>Kingdome</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne can subsist of it selfe, none hath more cause to <hi>Blesse God,</hi> then this <hi>Iland</hi> of ours, which <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God</hi> hath richly adornd with varietie of all things necessary for mans life &amp; welfare. As with <hi>Corne,</hi> and our<note n="*" place="margin">I meane <hi>Beere</hi> which in forreine parts is of more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme then wine. And to vs also in the vse, if there were not abuse is farre to be preferred.</note>
               <hi>Wine: Cattle, Wooll, Cloth, Tynne, Iron, Lead, Saffran, Waxe, Hoppes, Hydes, Tallow, Flaxe, Fowle, Fish,</hi> and many others: whereby, thanks be to <hi>God,</hi> the people of this Land, haue not onely <hi>Sufficient</hi> for their owne maintenance, but do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly <hi>Supply</hi> the wants of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Commerce</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome within it selfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The decay of the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of this Kingdom, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered Ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or apart.</note> and <hi>with Forreine Nations,</hi> consisting of so many rich Commodities; let vs consider them all <hi>Ioyntly,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177945:23"/> then some Principall of them <hi>Apart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ioyntly consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Trade, are the want of Mony, and the East-India stocke.</note>
               <hi>Iointly</hi> considered, the <hi>Causes</hi> of the decay of <hi>Trade</hi> in them, may be sayd either to be <hi>Deficient,</hi> or <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient. Deficient,</hi> either in the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> want of money in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; or the <hi>Particular</hi> want of the <hi>East-India stocke.</hi> I shewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what were the causes of the want of mony: and that the disaster vpon the <hi>East-India Trade</hi> is a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Cause</hi> thereof: but these are <hi>Both Causes</hi> of the <hi>Decay</hi> of <hi>Trade.</hi> For <hi>Money</hi> is the <hi>vitall spirit</hi> of <hi>trade,</hi> and if the <hi>Spirits faile,</hi> needes must the <hi>Body faint.</hi> And as the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of <hi>Trade</hi> seemeth to be <hi>Dead</hi> without the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Mony:</hi> so do also the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> without their <hi>Meanes</hi> of <hi>Trade.</hi> We say, that an <hi>Artizan</hi> or <hi>Workeman,</hi> cannot <hi>Worke</hi> without <hi>Tooles</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments:</hi> no more can a <hi>Merchant Trade without Money</hi> or meanes.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177945:23"/> And in the <hi>Want</hi> of so great a <hi>Stock,</hi> as is that of the <hi>East-India Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> of this <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> hath lost the vse of many of it <hi>Principall Members;</hi> by whose in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry, art, and action the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce</hi> thereof might wonderfully haue beene encre'st. The losse whereof, to him that is not wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blinde, is apparently sensible in the <hi>Drapery</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Poore</hi> are set on worke: and in all the other <hi>Trades</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> whereby the <hi>Subiects</hi> are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: and hath begot that great and generall <hi>Dampe</hi> and <hi>Deadnesse</hi> in all the <hi>Trades</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which wee vnhappily feele at this day.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Efficient causes</hi> of the <hi>Decay</hi> of <hi>Trade Iointly</hi> considered,<note place="margin">Or Vsury.</note>
               <note place="margin">Entituled a Tract against vsury, presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Vsury,</hi> or <hi>Vnnecessary Suits in Law.</hi> In the <hi>Former</hi> I am preuented, and my labour spared, by him that wrote a little treatise against <hi>Vsury:</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:177945:24"/> which it seeme's for <hi>Modesty</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseth to owe: Though I could wish, that those that deserue of the <hi>Publique</hi> were knowne to the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique:</hi> least they be serued as some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Batillus</hi> serued <hi>Virgil,</hi> and so be forc't too late to proclaime, <hi>Hos ego versiculos feci, tulit alter Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue a word onely to adde to his <hi>Vsury,</hi> that it is not an <hi>Vsury</hi> of <hi>Ten</hi> in the hundred only, that wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> but an <hi>Extortion</hi> also of 20. 30. 40. nay of <hi>Cento per Cento per Anno,</hi> as the <hi>Italians</hi> speake, giuen and taken on<note n="*" place="margin">A grieuous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse in certain Brokers about this City, who vpon the pawnes of the Poore, take this excessiue extortion. Of Litigious Law-suits.</note>
               <hi>Pledges</hi> and <hi>Pawnes,</hi> and that on <hi>Poore</hi> peoples labours, in <hi>London</hi> es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially: which is a biting <hi>Vsury</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, and a fearefull crying sinne before <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnnecessary Suites of Law</hi> are also <hi>Efficient Causes</hi> of the decay of Trade. Wherein certainely this <hi>Kingdome</hi> exceedeth all other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177945:24"/>
               <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in the world. As the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> is the <hi>Diadem</hi> of the KING, &amp; doth <hi>Stabilire Regis thronum,</hi> and <hi>Tribuere cuique suum:</hi> whereby <hi>Men</hi> may giue <hi>Caesar Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars,</hi> and <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: so is the <hi>Iustice</hi> of the KING, in the <hi>Sacred Person</hi> of HIS <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty,</hi> amongst other HIS <hi>Royall Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> an <hi>Embleme</hi> and <hi>Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Highest Maiesty;</hi> and it is an incomparable happinesse of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to haue such a <hi>Malchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec,</hi> a KING <hi>of Iustice, a</hi> KING <hi>of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither may I forget that <hi>Royall Testimony</hi> hereof, which is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be written in <hi>Letters of Gold,</hi> and thankefully to bee remembred of euery <hi>Tongue</hi> and <hi>Pen;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of a royal protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Star-chamber of His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties sincerity in Iustice.</note> whereof amongst others more worthy, it was also my happinesse to be <hi>Ocula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Auritus Testis:</hi> when HIS <hi>Maiesty</hi> in a <hi>Star-chamber</hi> assembly, lifting HIS <hi>Eye</hi> toward Heauen, &amp;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177945:25"/> laying HIS <hi>Hand</hi> on HIS <hi>Sonnes Head,</hi> made such a solemne <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station</hi> of HIS <hi>Sincerity</hi> in <hi>Iustice,</hi> as may serue for a matter of <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> and <hi>Imitation,</hi> to all the Kings on earth. Those that <hi>Went Before,</hi> and they that <hi>Followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> Those that <hi>Heard it then,</hi> and they that <hi>Heard of it since;</hi> sayd it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Nec vox hominem sonat, ô Deus certè!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If such then be the <hi>Iustice</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> how is it then that <hi>Trade</hi> is hindered by suits of <hi>Law?</hi> Herein <hi>Columellae's</hi> counsell is remarqueable, <hi>Principi prouidendum est,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Re Rustica.</note>
               <hi>ne legibus fundata ciuitas, legibus euertatur.</hi> There cannot be too much <hi>Iustice,</hi> there may be too much <hi>Law.</hi> For the vse of <hi>Iustice</hi> is cxcellent,<note place="margin">Honestè viuere: Alterum non laedere: Suum cuique tribuere. <hi>Iuris praecept.</hi>
               </note> in contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning men within the bonds of <hi>Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> and <hi>Honesty:</hi> in preseruing men from <hi>Iniury:</hi> and in maintayning euery mans <hi>Right and Proprietie.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:177945:25"/> But the abuse there-of is a most pernitious and dangerous surfeit in the <hi>Bodie</hi> of euery <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is our case in this <hi>Weale-publike:</hi> no <hi>Kingdome</hi> hath better <hi>Lawes;</hi> no <hi>Kingdome</hi> so full fraught with tedious, needlesse, endlesse, <hi>Suites</hi> of <hi>Law.</hi> For now this <hi>Liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandi</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and waxeth so fast, and groweth so great, that <hi>Suites</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> doe seeme immortall: time doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease them, and length of time would not determine them, if the wisedome of those <hi>Graue Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> did not put an end to the malice of the <hi>Litigants:</hi> as is now worthily obserued in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, to his honour and memorie that hath so happily begun the same.</p>
            <p>By the growth and greatnesse of which <hi>Suites,</hi> I say, a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of HIS Maiesties good and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177945:26"/> subiects are vexed, imprisoned impouerished and ouerthrowne: and whilst the <hi>Litigants</hi> striue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, another taketh away the <hi>Fish,</hi> and as it is in the <hi>Apologue,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to either of them an empty <hi>Shell.</hi> And thus mens time and meanes being spent in <hi>Law,</hi> which should be employed in <hi>Trade,</hi> trade is neglected, and the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> depriued, of the benefit that might be purchased and procured thereby.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the <hi>decay of Trade</hi> considered <hi>Ioyntly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Decay of trade con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered apart, in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Munition.</note> It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth now to consider them <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,</hi> in some principall parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Which may be reduced, to such as tend to the <hi>Fortification of the Kingdome,</hi> or <hi>Maintenance of Trade.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> are <hi>Ordinance</hi> and <hi>Munition:</hi> the too-too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon exportation whereof, hath taught vs wofull experience of an invaluable inconuenience thereby
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177945:26"/> which euery man is sensible of: and therefore I neede not <hi>presse</hi> it: I wish it did not <hi>Oppresse</hi> vs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Latter,</hi> I will referre to things essentiall, for the preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans life, as <hi>Victus</hi> and <hi>Vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> yet such of them also as doe aford wondrous variety of Trade, and may be termed the <hi>Nourceries</hi> thereof, as the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>shing</hi> and <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome.</hi> For on these two, all sorts of <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Tradesmen,</hi> haue some depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</p>
            <p>The inconuenience in the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Or in the Fishing.</note> is that <hi>Encroaching</hi> of <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> in <hi>Fishing</hi> vpon our <hi>Coasts:</hi> whereby not onely the <hi>Bread</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the subiects <hi>Mouth,</hi> but that infinite <hi>Wealth,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath made <hi>Proper</hi> and <hi>Peculiar</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Vs,</hi> is become <hi>Common</hi> vnto <hi>them.</hi> Whereby also, their <hi>Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> is wonderfully encrea'st, their <hi>Marriners</hi> are multiplied, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177945:27"/> exceeding great <hi>Trades</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into all parts of the Christian World. And Victuals commonly yeelding ready money, and tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of exportation thereof, the same hath redounded to an infinite enriching of their Countries with <hi>Treasure,</hi> exhausted out of these <hi>Mines</hi> of our's.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that a learned man of that side, pressing hard in a Treatise entituled <hi>Mare liberum,</hi> the Communitie and freedome of the <hi>Sea</hi> against the <hi>Portugall</hi> Trade into the <hi>East Indies;</hi> doth cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and obliquely, vnder the couert termes of <hi>Populi Romani littus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and maintaine, in the fift Chapter thereof, their <hi>Fishing</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Coasts.</hi> For thus hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, <hi>Nemo igitur potest à populo Romano ad littus maris accedere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiberi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maere liberum. cap. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>&amp; retia siccare, &amp; alia facere, quae semel omnes homines in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum sibi licere voluerunt.</hi> And
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177945:27"/> againe, <hi>Exteris ius piscandi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eodem cap. p. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>vbique immune esse debet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To part of which Treatise, there is an answere entituled, <hi>De Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Maris,</hi> to which I referre those that desire further satisfaction in this matter. But in my iudgement, which I submit to better iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Author of <hi>Mare libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> though otherwise very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, strayneth his Arguments for that purpose beyond their strength. For <hi>Ius</hi> is said to be <hi>scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> or <hi>Non scriptum.</hi> And <hi>Non scriptum</hi> is <hi>Consuetudo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Arte iuris cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suetudo non minus est species iuris, quàm ius scriptum.</hi> And by both these, the <hi>Proprieties</hi> of the Seas may be proued, to belong to those <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Countries,</hi> to which they are next <hi>Adiacent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Custome,</hi> the examples of our Neighbor Countries round about vs are frequent. As of <hi>Coeldine, Groeneland, Norway,</hi> and <hi>Friseland,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:177945:28"/> vnder the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Denmarke. Tunny fishing</hi> vnder the the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Medina.</hi> The <hi>Gulfe of Venice</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>Seignory.</hi> And many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I might instance: In all which there is no liberty of fishing, but by <hi>Speciall priuiledge</hi> had from those <hi>Princes</hi> to whō the same belongeth. Which being so, we may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the <hi>Poet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hor.</note>
               <hi>Cùm ventum ad verum est, sensus moresque repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Law</hi> it selfe, it is not hard to produce some of his owne Authors against himselfe. As the <hi>Emperour Leo:</hi> of whom hee thus speaketh,<note place="margin">Mare liberum p. <hi>25.</hi> Nouella Leo. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Voluit</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hoc est, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stibula maritima eorum esse propria, qui oram habitarent; ibique eos ius piscandi habere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also <hi>Rodericus Suarius,</hi> whose testimony because he was a <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> he produceth against the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals</hi> in the end of his fift Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: whom, if hee had pleased,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177945:28"/> hee might also haue thus cited: <hi>Redditus piscariarum consueti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roderic. Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius de vsu Maris. consil. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>vt est gabella, seu aliud tributum solui consuetum, de his quae in mari piscato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res faciunt, seu à mercatoribus de his quae emunt aut vendunt, Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pibus conceduntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I will onely adde that of <hi>Bartolus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Insulae ff. de iu. &amp;. L. Caesar. ff. de public.</note> whom the <hi>Ciuilians</hi> call <hi>Iuris Lucernam,</hi> thus speaking: <hi>Vt Insulae in mari proximè adiacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, sic &amp; mare ipsum ad Centum vs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que milliaria pro territorio districtú<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que illius regionis cui proxime appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquat, assignatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rest that the Author of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re liberum</hi> enforceth, of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity and Freedome of the <hi>Sea</hi> to all <hi>Nations,</hi> he vnderstandeth of matters in question, betweene the <hi>Portugals</hi> and those of his <hi>Nation,</hi> concerning their <hi>East India Trade,</hi> and not of their <hi>Fishing</hi> vpon our <hi>Coasts.</hi> Which <hi>Question</hi> in my iudgement, being <hi>out of question</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:177945:29"/> were better determined by <hi>Action</hi> then <hi>Disputation:</hi> It being a <hi>Royalty</hi> of the King, and a <hi>Regall Priuiledge</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> assigned by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Or in the Clothing.</note>From the <hi>Fishing</hi> come wee to the <hi>Clothing</hi> or <hi>Drapery</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome:</hi> the consideration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is of very high consequence, and concerneth both the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and the <hi>Subiect, Noble</hi> and <hi>Ignoble;</hi> euen al sorts, and callings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men in this <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> For this is sayd to bee a <hi>Flower</hi> of the Kings <hi>Crowne,</hi> the <hi>Dowry</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> the chiefe <hi>Reuenue</hi> of the King. This is a <hi>Bound</hi> to fortifie, and a <hi>Bond</hi> to knit the subiects together in their seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall societies. This is the <hi>Gold</hi> of our <hi>Ophir,</hi> the <hi>Milke</hi> &amp; <hi>Hony</hi> of our <hi>Canaan,</hi> the <hi>Indies</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> and therefore <hi>Desire's</hi> &amp; <hi>Deserue's</hi> to be had in an euerlasting remēbrance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Draperies</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:177945:29"/> are termed <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New.</hi> By the <hi>Old;</hi> are vnderstood <hi>Broad Cloathes, Bayes</hi> and <hi>Kersies:</hi> By the <hi>New; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuanoes, Serges, Sayes,</hi> and other <hi>Manufactures</hi> of <hi>wooll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Causes</hi> then of the <hi>Decay</hi> of <hi>Trade</hi> in these <hi>Draperies,</hi> are either <hi>Domestique</hi> or <hi>Forreine.</hi> The <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestique causes,</hi> are some <hi>past,</hi> some <hi>Present. Those Past,</hi> are apparent in the late disturbance of the Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trade; which is so obuious to euery man, that I had rather <hi>Passe by it,</hi> then <hi>Presse vpon it,</hi> because it is <hi>Past:</hi> and I would to God that so were the effects of it also. In charitie wee may thinke it was <hi>Good</hi> in the <hi>Purpose,</hi> though it proued <hi>Ill</hi> in the <hi>Practise.</hi> For thereby the <hi>Drape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> are much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minished, and the forreine aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and aduantaged. The quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of which last, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly few or none, but now they exceede our highest numbers issu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177945:30"/> out of the land: as by a colecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, which my selfe made in those part, by HIS <hi>Maiestie,</hi> speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cōmand, in the time of <hi>Secretary Winwoods</hi> seruice, may appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>These Present,</hi> may be discern'd in the <hi>Cloth-trade,</hi> either vnder the <hi>Clothier,</hi> or vnder the <hi>Merchant.</hi> Vnder the <hi>Clothier,</hi> either by <hi>Ill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> or <hi>False sealing</hi> the Cloth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The decay of Clothing vnder the Clothier, or vnder the Merchant.</note>For the making of good and true Cloth, many excellent lawes haue bin inuented &amp; enacted by the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of this land, from time to time. And the Statute of 4.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </note> of the <hi>King Cap.</hi> 2. doth seeme to bee an <hi>Epitome</hi> or <hi>Compendiary</hi> of all the former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in this kinde.<note place="margin">Vnder the Clothier, by ill making, or false sealing of Cloth.</note> In this Statute is prescribed, the true breadth, and length, and waight, that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the making of a true and perfect Cloth, Kersie or Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. If a Clothier make a Cloth of lesse waight, then is set downe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177945:30"/> in the said Statute, he offendeth in <hi>Quantitie:</hi> If of lesse breadth, or length, or of forbidden kindes of wooll, hee offendeth in <hi>Qualitie.</hi> If a Clothier offend in <hi>Neither</hi> of these by his <hi>Owne Act,</hi> yet he may offend in <hi>Both,</hi> by his <hi>Instruments</hi> or <hi>Workmen:</hi> Either by the <hi>Weauers,</hi> in <hi>not putting in</hi> the stuffe <hi>at the making;</hi> or by the <hi>Tuckers</hi> in <hi>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out</hi> the stuffe <hi>after the making</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>A Cloth also may be well made; &amp; yet false sealed. A Cloth may be said to be lawfully made, when it is truly sealed. For althogh it may be impossible to make some Clothes, iust of those quantities and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties prescribed by the Statute; as the <hi>Clothiers</hi> terme is, <hi>A man cannot cast a cloth in a mould:</hi> yet I hope, they will giue me leaue to say, that it is possible that a Cloth may bee true sealed, though false made. And then a <hi>Cloth ill made,</hi> and <hi>true
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177945:31"/> sealed,</hi> whereby the buyer may see what hee hath for his money, may bee said to bee a good or lawfull Cloth according to the Statute.</p>
            <p>Now the execution of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute for <hi>Searching</hi> and <hi>Sealing of Clothes,</hi> seemeth to be referred to two sorts of men: which are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Aulnager</hi> or <hi>Searcher.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> may seeme originally to haue beene an Officer appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that purpose, as well by the <hi>Notation</hi> of the name, as by some <hi>Ancient Statutes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.6. &amp;c.</note> For <hi>Aulne,</hi> and <hi>Aulnage,</hi> and <hi>Aulnagier,</hi> are all <hi>French</hi> words, taken from the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring of Cloth. And thence it is, that in that tong they are wont to say <hi>Aulner draps</hi> to measure Clothes, by a <hi>Trope</hi> taken from the <hi>Instrument</hi> by which they are <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because the care of the <hi>Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> is committed to so <hi>Noble and Honourable a Personage,</hi> that will
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177945:31"/> not suffer any abuse in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that office: and the said Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 4. <hi>Iacobi,</hi> and the former Statutes of 39. and 43. <hi>Elizabethae</hi> doe referre the <hi>Searching</hi> and <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of Clothes, to certaine <hi>Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seers</hi> or <hi>Searchers,</hi> so called by the said <hi>Stautes,</hi> I will proceede vnto them.</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as <hi>Execution</hi> is the <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties speech in Parliament. In <hi>Iune</hi> 1611.</note> as HIS <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie</hi> in high <hi>High wisdoma</hi> admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth: and the <hi>Prudence,</hi> and <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> haue beene very great in deuising and enacting such good lawes from time to time, as might tend to the encrease and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of the <hi>Drapery</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome:</hi> If therefore now any thing bee amisse therein, it must needs come through the want of <hi>Execution</hi> of those <hi>Lawes. Hincillae lachrymae!</hi> This <hi>Bonum</hi> according to HIS <hi>Maiesties Regall rule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eeadem Oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Regia.</note> is not <hi>Benè.</hi> For these <hi>Ouerseers</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177945:32"/>
               <hi>Searchers</hi> being silly Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and generally not expert in the <hi>mystery</hi> of making of Cloth: in the <hi>Search</hi> whereof, there is as much neede of skill as in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: for how should they finde the fault, that know not how it is committed? These Searchers I say, thus being ignorant and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull in their offices, and nelgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent also, (in which last, it hath beene againe and againe confest, that they haue set the seales of their office, to Clothes they neuer search't nor saw) needs must there be a great abuse, in the <hi>Execution</hi> of those good <hi>Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay I would I could not say, how much our Nation hath beene vpbrayded by the people of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine parts with this abuse, that the <hi>Searchers Seales</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are <hi>bought</hi> and <hi>sold</hi> as in a market, and put on the Clothes by the <hi>Tuckers,</hi> and other the seruants of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177945:32"/>
               <hi>Clothiers,</hi> as if the same had beene lawfully <hi>Searched</hi> and <hi>Sealed</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Statute;</hi> when as the <hi>Searchers Eye</hi> neuer so much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the <hi>Clothes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the people of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands</hi> are so exact, that you shall neuer find any of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Clothes false <hi>Search't</hi> or <hi>Seal'd.</hi> For you shall haue a <hi>Seale</hi> set vpon the Cloth when it commeth from the <hi>Weauers:</hi> another when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth frō the <hi>Tuckers:</hi> another when it cōmeth from the <hi>Dyers:</hi> and that by men of good quality, appointed for that purpose in euery <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Towne</hi> where Cloth is made, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Curemasters:</hi> so called from the <hi>Care</hi> they ought, and doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, in the execution of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: wherein indeed they are so exact, that you shall neuer finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Seales</hi> aforesaid, set to any manner of <hi>false</hi> or <hi>Defectiue</hi> Cloth.</p>
            <p>For indeed the <hi>Searcher</hi> being a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177945:33"/>
               <hi>Sworne Officer,</hi> ought to be as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes without exceptiō betwixt man and man: that when a man seeth the <hi>Searchers seale</hi> set vpon the Cloth, it should serue as a true <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat</hi> of the true making thereof. It is a great impiety before <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> to be a false witnesse in any case: but these <hi>Searchers</hi> are false witnesses <hi>Ipse facto,</hi> when they doe <hi>Testifie</hi> to the world by their <hi>Seales,</hi> that those Clothes are <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> which indeede are vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>False.</hi> And which aggrauateth the matter yet more, that <hi>the Kings Seale of Armes,</hi> wich is <hi>testis omni exceptione maior,</hi> should also bee set to Clothes thus <hi>Falsely searched</hi> &amp; <hi>sealed;</hi> whereby not onely <hi>the Kings Subiects,</hi> but the <hi>Strangers</hi> also in <hi>Forreine parts</hi> are deceiued, is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grosse and grieuous abuse.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An example of Clothes ill made, searched and sealed.</note>Amongst other abuses of this kinde, one precedent come's to my minde, of <hi>Ten</hi> Clothes bought not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177945:33"/> long since by a <hi>Merchant,</hi> of a <hi>Clothier</hi> of <hi>Wiltshire.</hi> Which Cloathes were all <hi>Sealed</hi> by the <hi>Searchers</hi> of that place, for good &amp; true, according to the Statute. But being tried by the <hi>Merchant-Buyer,</hi> and afterward by the <hi>Sworne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer</hi> of the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> were found so defectiue in length, breadth and waight, that where these <hi>Ten</hi> Clothes cost but 60. <hi>lib.</hi> or thereabouts, the faults in these <hi>Ten</hi> Clothes came to neere 20. <hi>lib.</hi> which was one third part of the value of the Cloth. And it being a notable contempt of the law, the <hi>Lords</hi> of HIS <hi>Maiesties most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Priuie Councell</hi> were infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thereof; who were pleased to send downe a <hi>Messenger</hi> into that <hi>County,</hi> and fetch't vp both the <hi>Clothier</hi> and <hi>Searchers,</hi> who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily vnder-went the Condigne Censure of the Lords.</p>
            <p>Vnder the <hi>Merchant</hi> also the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177945:34"/>
               <hi>Cloth-trade</hi> suffereth both at <hi>Home</hi> and <hi>Abroad.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Cloth trade suffereth vnder the Merchant, At home and abroad. At Home by Exportation of the Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, or Imposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Charge.</note>
               <hi>At Home,</hi> by <hi>Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Materials,</hi> either of <hi>Woolles</hi> or <hi>Wooll-fels</hi> from the <hi>Sea coasts</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> or by <hi>Ouer-lading</hi> the <hi>Cloth-trade,</hi> either with any <hi>generall</hi> or <hi>speciall</hi> charge.</p>
            <p>The <hi>latter</hi> I cannot pretermit: for as the chiefe waight of the <hi>Cloth-trade</hi> lyeth on the <hi>Merchants-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers;</hi> so also is the burthen of charge most felt vnder that <hi>Trade.</hi> For the <hi>Impositions and Imprest mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> by them layd vpon the <hi>Cloth,</hi> for defraying the charge of their Gouernment, and payment of their Debts; haue driuen many good <hi>Merchants</hi> out of the Trade, and giuen the <hi>Clothiers</hi> occasion to complaine of want of <hi>Buyers,</hi> and thrust the Trade it selfe more and more into the <hi>Strangers</hi> hands.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abroad by vnfit Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note>And <hi>abroad,</hi> by the <hi>vnfit place of Residence,</hi> which the <hi>Merchants-Aduenturers</hi> are fallen vpon in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177945:34"/>
               <hi>Holland.</hi> Whither they goe with great perill of Shippe and Goods: And where they come farre short of that they hoped for; and of that quicke and ample vent of their Cloth they found in <hi>Zeeland.</hi> The <hi>Agitation</hi> of which remooue; is vehemently suspected to haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the <hi>Merchants</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> to procure <hi>Priuiledges</hi> of the <hi>States Generall</hi> to <hi>Incorporate</hi> themselues, and <hi>keepe Courts,</hi> to confront the <hi>Merchant Aduenturers;</hi> which they neuer did before: To haue drawne the<note n="*" place="margin">That is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating for the faults thereof</note>
               <hi>Taring</hi> of Cloth into <hi>Holland,</hi> where the <hi>Buyers</hi> are in some sort <hi>Iudges</hi> &amp; <hi>Parties;</hi> which before was in the <hi>Mart-towne.</hi> where the <hi>Seller</hi> was present: And lastly, to haue hastned the great <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> All which are matters of moment, and concerne the <hi>Cloth-trade</hi> verie much, and whereof the <hi>English Factors</hi> there residing doe generally complaine:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177945:35"/> Yet <hi>These</hi> I rather instance then vrge: leauing the further Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof to their own relation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Forreine cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the Drapery, are the warres and the great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </note>Now the <hi>Forreine Causes</hi> of the decay of the <hi>Drapery</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> are either <hi>Generall,</hi> as the warrs in <hi>Germany:</hi> or <hi>Speciall,</hi> as the <hi>Great Imposition</hi> lately laide vpon our Cloth in <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>Former,</hi> the Course of Trade is stopt and hindered, that Merchants cannot passe without perill from place to place: and the monies become so variable, that when a Merchant hath sold his Cloth, and hopeth to haue gained something thereby; by that time that the terme for payment is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, hee receiueth lesse in value then the Clothes cost, by the <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> and <hi>Rising</hi> of the monies.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>latter,</hi> the <hi>Merchants</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> are discouraged, whereby many of them haue giuen ouer their Trades, which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they followed in ample man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177945:35"/> in our <hi>English</hi> Clothes bought of the <hi>Merchants-Aduenturers</hi> from time to time: which hath also ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the aduancement of the <hi>Dutch Draperies;</hi> because the same are freed of all manner of charge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. III.</hi> Of gouerned Trade, and therein of <hi>Monopoly.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HItherto the <hi>Matter of Trade</hi> hath beene considered in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> and <hi>Merchandize:</hi> the <hi>Forme</hi> followeth, and that either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of <hi>Gouernment,</hi> or <hi>Want of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment</hi> in trade. <hi>Gouernment</hi> is a representation of the <hi>Maiestie</hi> and <hi>Authoritie</hi> of <hi>the</hi> KING. The sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that is honoured with <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> is inuested with part of the KINGS <hi>Honour.</hi> The <hi>Trades</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> which <hi>by</hi> HIS <hi>Maiesties especiall Grace and Fauour</hi> are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnder <hi>Order and Gouernment</hi> into <hi>Corporations, Companies,</hi> and <hi>Societies,</hi> doe certainely much
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:177945:36"/>
               <hi>Aduaunce</hi> and <hi>Aduantage</hi> the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> and farre excell the trades of any other forreine Merchants in their vngo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned trades.</p>
            <p>But as the <hi>Vse</hi> of <hi>Gouernment</hi> is excellent for the restraint of vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and disorderly trade: so the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse</hi> therof is as inconuenient, if at any time the same be too strict, and come within the compasse of a <hi>Monopoly.</hi> And because the name and nature of <hi>Monopoly,</hi> is more <hi>talk't of,</hi> then well <hi>vnderstood</hi> of many; and some thinke that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of trade into <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,</hi> is a kinde of <hi>Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing</hi> and restraint of trade: I haue thought it not vnseasonable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow some speciall paines in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent inuestigation thereof. Not that I would haue the trade of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> so circumscribed or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to any, that others of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> Subiects should bee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177945:36"/> depriued of the libertie thereof; but that vpon equall &amp; reasonable termes, trading vnder <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Gouernment,</hi> without that ill tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Monopoly,</hi> the KINGS <hi>high way of trade</hi> should be opened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all.</p>
            <p>The name therefore of <hi>Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in our English tongue, is deriued, as the learned know, of the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: whence also the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine word <hi>Monopolium</hi> is borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Some deriue it of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Solus,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Vendo,</hi> to sell alone. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Solus,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor,</hi> to cōuerse alone. Other of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Solus,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Ciuitas, quasi vnica negotiatio in Ciuitate.</hi> But all these agree in one meaning of the word, that it is <hi>Singularis Negotiatio,</hi> a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting of <hi>Commerse</hi> from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall course and vse thereof, into the hands of some few, to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and others preiudice. I also find many <hi>definitions</hi> of <hi>Monopolies:</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:177945:37"/> and a great question among the <hi>Ciuilians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Huiusmodi contractus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta emptionis &amp; conductionis similitudine confundebatur, vt vix ac ne vix quidem à iuris consultis internosci pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit. Hottom. ad tit. in lib. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.</hi> De Rep. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> whether a <hi>Monopoly</hi> may bee exercised of one alone; and whether it consist aswell in <hi>Locatio Conductio,</hi> as they speak, as in <hi>Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Venditio.</hi> Which last is out of question with all. And of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, I finde an instance in <hi>Aristotle</hi> of <hi>Thales Milesius</hi> his <hi>Monopolie:</hi> who by his knowledge in <hi>Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> fore-seeing one yeare in the winter, that there would bee great plentie of <hi>Oyles</hi> the next yeare, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before-hand all the places and engins for making of <hi>Oyle</hi> through both the Ilands of <hi>Melazo</hi> &amp; <hi>Chius,</hi> and afterwards let out the same a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at his owne pleasure &amp; price. In the same place hee maketh also mention of another, who bought vp all the Iron in <hi>Sicilia,</hi> which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he sold againe, and made one hundred <hi>Talents</hi> of that which cost him but fiftie. Amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I will take the <hi>definition</hi> of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177945:37"/>
               <hi>Althusius</hi> for all the rest.<note place="margin">Politic. cap. <hi>31.</hi> n. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> saith he, <hi>Est Commercium emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, vendendi, permutandiue, à paucis vel vno etiam vsurpatum, reliquis ciuibus praeceptum, quo pretia augen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cum lucro negotiantis, &amp; reliquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum damno.</hi> That is, <hi>Monopoly is a kind of Commerce, in buying, selling, changing or bartering, vsurped by a few, and sometimes but by one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and fore-stalled from all others, to the Gaine of the Monopolist, and to the Detriment of other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts then of a <hi>Monopolie</hi> are twaine. The restraint of the liberty of <hi>Commerce</hi> to some one or few: and the setting of the price at the pleasure of the <hi>Monopolian</hi> to his priuate benefit, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of the publique. Vpon which two <hi>Hinges</hi> euery <hi>Monopoly</hi> turneth. And these two parts are respectiuely repugnant to the two fundamentall requisites of al good
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177945:38"/> Lawes: to wit, <hi>Equitie</hi> and <hi>Vtility.</hi> For it is against <hi>Equitie,</hi> that one Member of a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> should bee more free then another of equall ranke and condition. And what can be more contrary to <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Vtility,</hi> then that some one or few persons, should sway the price of any thing vsefull to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> to their owne <hi>Enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and the <hi>Common Losse</hi> of other men? And heere it is to bee well obserued, that vnlesse these two parts concurre in a <hi>Monopoly:</hi> it cannot truely and properly bee so called, nor ought it so to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thusius polit. cap. <hi>32.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib. Decianus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ract. crim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. <hi>21.</hi> Meno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>569.</hi>
               </note> And therefore <hi>Althusius</hi> following <hi>Decianus,</hi> saith well of that restraint of the <hi>Cōmon Liberty,</hi> which we call <hi>Suit of Mill:</hi> which compelleth men to vse this or that <hi>Mill to grinde corne,</hi> and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: that it doth onely <hi>Sapere Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolium,</hi> Sauour of Monopoly: but that it is not truly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177945:38"/> a <hi>Monopoly.</hi> For in that case of <hi>Suit of Mill,</hi> vnlesse there be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Tolle or recompence exacted for grinding, then at other Milles, it falleth onely within the first part of a Monopoly, to wit, <hi>of the Restraint of the Publike Liberty;</hi> but not within compasse of the other part, <hi>the Setting of the Price.</hi> But for this <hi>Restraint of the Publike Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Commerce,</hi> it may bee so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by <hi>the Wisdome of the State,</hi> that it may bee both <hi>Lawfull</hi> and <hi>Beneficiall</hi> to the <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> Which assertion, because it may seeme strange to some, I will make euident by <hi>Good Authoritie</hi> and <hi>Examples. Peter Martyr</hi> that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous light of the Churches of the Gospell,<note place="margin">P. Mart. in <hi>I.</hi> Reg. c. <hi>10.</hi> &amp;c.</note> defendeth the restraint of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that none should buy <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Egypt</hi> without his Licence, to bee Lawfull. And of this kinde is the <hi>Preemption of Tinne</hi> heere in <hi>England,</hi> granted by HIS <hi>Maiesties
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177945:39"/> Gracious Letters Patents</hi> to some few, with restraint of all others: which I dare boldly affirme is not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but very <hi>beneficiall</hi> also to this <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> For therby our <hi>Thrice Noble Prince</hi> receiueth a good reuenue, and the <hi>Tinne</hi> of this Land is sold for many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds a yeare more in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein parts, then otherwise it would, to the great increase of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon stocke</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Also the Law of this <hi>Realme</hi> alloweth, that if any man inuent a new Art, beneficiall to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> hee may haue a Patent to vse that Art solely, with restraint of all others for seuen yeares: as well in recompence of his industry, as for the incouragement of others, to studie and inuent things profitable for the publique <hi>Symbiosis.</hi> The <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> restraine from the exercise of sundry <hi>Crafts,</hi> all such as haue not serued an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentishood
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177945:39"/> vnto that <hi>Art</hi> which they would exercise: to the end that those <hi>Artes</hi> might be brought to better perfection, and the things made, might be good and seruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for those that buy and vse them.</p>
            <p>The restraint of the <hi>Publique Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie,</hi> is sometimes exercised by <hi>Priuate Authoritie:</hi> sometimes by <hi>Publique.</hi> Which distinction is made by the <hi>Emperour Zeno. Iube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ne quis pro sua authoritate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cod. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tit. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>vel sacro elicito rescripto, &amp;c. Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um audeat exercere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>former</hi> is practised, when any one or more, haue by their owne priuate contracts, gotten any Commoditie or matter of <hi>Commerce,</hi> wholly into their owne hands. Of this kinde are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples aboue cited out of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>latter</hi> is, when by Publike authority, the liberty of the subiect
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177945:40"/> is restrained: which is done, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the <hi>Prerogatiue of the</hi> KING: sometimes by <hi>Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Former,</hi> by dispensing with a generall Law in some point, and applying the dispensation to some one or few, with restraint of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The <hi>Latter,</hi> by prohibiting all, but some one or few persons to vse the benefit of the Law in some point or other.</p>
            <p>For dispensing with the Lawes, it is without question, that <hi>the</hi> KING hath power to dispence with a <hi>Penal Law,</hi> when it prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that which is not <hi>Malum in se.</hi> For the <hi>Parliament</hi> hauing made a <hi>Statute</hi> with intent of the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good:</hi> yet the same by reason of something not foreseene at the making of the Law, may proue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie preiudiciall in the Execution. And then the <hi>Malum prohibitum,</hi> as the <hi>Lawyers</hi> speake, may be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177945:40"/> with by <hi>the</hi> KING. Thus the <hi>Parliament</hi> hauing prohibited the exportation of white Clothes vndrest aboue the price of foure pound the Cloth:<note place="margin">33. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> the obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Statute was found by experience to be very preiudiciall to the Trade, and free vent of the Cloth in forreine parts. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> granted a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Licence to the Fellowship of the <hi>Merchant Aduenturers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno <hi>6.</hi> Eliz.</note> to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port all sorts of white Clothes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drest, with a <hi>Non obstante</hi> to that Statute. And although all other men stood lyable to the Statute still, and were restrained, yet the <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie</hi> that hereby arose to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> did farre exceede the restraint of the <hi>Publike Libertie.</hi> For within few yeares after the granting of this Licence, the vent of Cloth in forreine parts increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to twice as much, as formerly it was during the strict obseruation
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177945:41"/> of the Statute. Other like dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations of Statutes, I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: as that of the 28. <hi>H.</hi> 8. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the retailing of <hi>Gasgoigne Wines</hi> at two pence a quart: which is dispensed with, by a Licence to the <hi>Company of the Vintners:</hi> but these may suffice for euery mans vnderstanding of this kinde of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Prohibition by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> such is the Act whereby all the subiects of this Realme, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such as are of the Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Muscouy Company,</hi> are forbidden to trade into any part of <hi>Russia.</hi> Also that of 3. <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Artizan Skinners,</hi> whereby all but the <hi>Company</hi> are forbidden to buy and retaile some sorts of Skinnes. In these and the like, the <hi>Parliament</hi> maketh restraint of the <hi>Common liberty of Commerce,</hi> and the same restraint is againe relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, not vnto all, but to some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177945:41"/> or <hi>Corporations</hi> by <hi>speciall Exercise and Prouiso</hi> of the Act of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Later kinde of Restraint by Publique Authority,</hi> is when that which seemeth by the Lawe to be free to al, is by some <hi>Patent or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of the Prince,</hi> prohibited to all, sauing some certaine <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> or persons specially excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and authorized in the same <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> or <hi>Proclamation.</hi> Of this kind are generally reputed all <hi>Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Merchants,</hi> which are not confirmed by <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi> Which are generally reputed to carry with them a restraint to others, of that <hi>Liberty,</hi> which the Law doth seeme to offer to all in point of <hi>Commerce.</hi> Whence it is that so many pleade the <hi>Freedome</hi> of subiects, and <hi>Presse</hi> or rather <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse</hi> that plea of equity, that it is equall that all subiects should bee alike free to bee Merchants in all
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177945:42"/> Trades. To whom I answer, that first there is no good <hi>Equality</hi> in it, because it is against the <hi>Publique Vtility,</hi> that all should bee Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants at their pleasure. For that's not equall, that may seeme profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to one, and bee hurtfull to many. <hi>Atque ipsa vtilitas iusti propè mater &amp; aequi,</hi> as <hi>Horace</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. And yet what point of <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is broken, when the freedome of Societies is so carryed, that it is open to all men vpon equall termes; that is to say, either by ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or purchase? Otherwise it were very vnequall, that one man should serue for his freedome, or buy the same: and another man should haue it for nothing. If this point were well thought vpon, I presume the <hi>Gracious Grants and priuiledges</hi> of HIS <hi>Maiestie,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vpon <hi>Societies,</hi> would not seeme so much a <hi>Restraint</hi> of the <hi>Common liberty,</hi> as a prudent orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177945:42"/> and accommodating thereof vnto the <hi>Publique Vtility.</hi> For it hath euer beene a <hi>Policy</hi> of this <hi>State,</hi> to reduce the <hi>Trades</hi> of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> into <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations</hi> and <hi>Societies,</hi> for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Trade, by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of order and gouernment: well foreseeing that there cannot bee any greater <hi>Bane</hi> to a <hi>Well-gouerned Common-wealth,</hi> then <hi>Ill-gouerned and Disorderly Trade.</hi> Whereof I shall haue fitter occasion to speake in the next Chapter, when I come to treat of the Inconueniences of the want of gouernment in Trade. So that in this case the general rule must be this; that such a <hi>Restraint</hi> of the <hi>Publique Liberty,</hi> as is before mentioned, is alwayes to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when the same is recompenced with a <hi>Publique Vtility.</hi> According to that of <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus.</note>
               <hi>Omne magnum exemplum habet in se aliquid iniqui, quod vtilitate publica contra singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177945:43"/> compensatur.</hi> Also the liberty that the Law seemeth to giue the subiects in Trade, is to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, of imploiment <hi>Within the Kingdome,</hi> not <hi>Without the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> For what liberty can a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Law,</hi> giue to a <hi>Forrein Trade</hi> vnder a <hi>Forreine Iurisdiction,</hi> when the liberty or restraint thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth vpon those <hi>Forreine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States</hi> where that Trade is tollerated? Therfore the <hi>Law</hi> may giue the subiect Liberty <hi>Within the Land,</hi> but it is the KING that must enable men to trade <hi>Without the Land.</hi> For all the <hi>Trades</hi> of the <hi>Merchants</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> into <hi>Forrein countries,</hi> are grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Amity</hi> of the KING, and the <hi>Treaties of Peace</hi> contracted by <hi>the</hi> KING, with the <hi>Kings and Rulers</hi> of those <hi>forreine parts,</hi> at his owne charge, and by HIS own Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without the assistance of HIS <hi>Parliament.</hi> And therefore it hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177945:43"/> good congruity, that <hi>the</hi> KING by HIS like Authority, may haue the disposing and ordering of such HIS contracts at his owne pleasure.</p>
            <p>The second part of <hi>Monopoly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, of the <hi>Setting of the Price</hi> at the pleasure of the <hi>Monopolist,</hi> to his <hi>Priuate gaine,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Publique losse.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cod.</hi> 4.59.</note> This <hi>Gothofredus</hi> calleth <hi>the Forme</hi> of a <hi>Monopoly.</hi> And in truth it is the very <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> thereof. And he or they that haue this power ouer the price of the thing they negotiate, may well be said according to the notation of <hi>Monopoly,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>conuerse alone.</hi> For in so doing, they so liue, as none can liue by them, in respect of their singuler gaine in this kinde: Contrary to that honest Prouerbiall rule of the Dutch, that men must <hi>Leuen ende Laeten Leuen:</hi> So liue as other men may Liue by them. But here I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177945:44"/> cannot but discharge all those <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> of this part of <hi>Monopoly,</hi> which afford to euery particuler Trader thereof, the managing of his owne stocke, in buying and selling as hee can, without any combination with others. In which it is as impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as vnusuall, for any to haue command of the price of their <hi>Commodities:</hi> because there is such a multitude of Traders of thē; and euery man is at liberty to buy or sell, without any rule by any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall order, or meanes to hold one price. But the greatest suspition of <hi>Monopoly</hi> in <hi>Corporations,</hi> is in such as Trade in <hi>Ioint stockes.</hi> Whereof if there be any that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in a <hi>Ioint stocke,</hi> and hath the <hi>Sole</hi> buying or selling of any <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity,</hi> and buy and sell the same <hi>Iointly,</hi> as by one person or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon factor, such is guilty of <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177945:44"/>
            <p>For <hi>particuler men,</hi> they may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so commit <hi>Monopolizing:</hi> either by procuring <hi>Patents</hi> by misinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the <hi>State,</hi> for the <hi>Sole Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting</hi> or <hi>Exporting,</hi> buying or sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at their owne prises, to the restraint of the <hi>Common Libertie,</hi> and the <hi>Publique Vtility</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> or else when some one or few, without any Authoritie, doe ioine together to engrosse and buy in a Commodity, and sell it out againe at their owne price. Of the former kinde, are those <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues</hi> of crying <hi>Monopolies,</hi> which HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> in HIS <hi>High Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Grace</hi> damned in HIS <hi>Princely Proclamation</hi> of the tenth of <hi>Iuly</hi> last, in the xix. yeare of HIS <hi>Maiesties most happy Reigne ouer this Kingdome:</hi> Many of which were abused in the <hi>Practise,</hi> from that which they appeared to be in the <hi>Institution.</hi> And here a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty question occurreth. When a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177945:45"/>
               <hi>Patent</hi> is granted to a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, so as he or they haue power to licence others to exercise some kinde of <hi>Commerce</hi> solely, and consequently with command of the price: the questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, who is then the <hi>Monopolian,</hi> whether the <hi>Patentees,</hi> or their <hi>Assignes?</hi> In this case I suppose, that both the one and the other commit <hi>Monopoly.</hi> For first, the <hi>Patentees</hi> make their price at their pleasure vpon their <hi>Assignes,</hi> and they againe vpon the <hi>subiects.</hi> So that here is <hi>Monopoly</hi> vpon <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly:</hi> like your <hi>Salt</hi> vpon <hi>Salt, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest</hi> vpon <hi>Interest,</hi> or the <hi>Decompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>situm</hi> in <hi>Grammer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the latter, some sorts of Trades-men in <hi>London,</hi> are said to offend. Which being matters of Generall note, and willing to auoid offence, I will passe by such parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. And this shall suffice for the <hi>Definition</hi> and <hi>Distribution</hi> of <hi>Monopoly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:177945:45"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. IIII.</hi> Of want of Gouernment in Trade.</head>
            <p>SVch is the <hi>Forme of Trade</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered in the <hi>Strict Vse</hi> or <hi>Abuse</hi> of <hi>Gouernment,</hi> by way of <hi>Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> It now remaineth briefely to shew the <hi>Too Loose Vse</hi> thereof, by <hi>Vngouerned Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Maxime</hi> in the <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,</hi> that <hi>Rectum est Index sui &amp; obliqui.</hi> And the want of <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> cannot better be demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then by the benefit of <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it selfe. For thereby the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> hath beene much aduantaged, both in the encrease of the natiue Commodities of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and the aduancement of their vse and price in <hi>Forreine parts:</hi> and also in keeping the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177945:46"/> wares at a moderate rate within this <hi>Kingdome.</hi> This will be yet more perspicuous, if we cast our eye first vpon the seueral <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Merchants</hi> which trade <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gouernment:</hi> and then on those which trade <hi>without Gouernment.</hi> For <hi>Contraria iuxta se posita, magis elucescunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers.</note>In the first place therefore consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we that <hi>Ancient</hi> and heretofore <hi>Famous fellowship</hi> of the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers of England.</hi> Hath it not by their politique rule and order, eaten out the <hi>Societie</hi> of the <hi>Hans-townes</hi> of <hi>Germanie</hi> and the <hi>Merchants</hi> of the <hi>Entercourse</hi> of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> in those trades, which a long time they enioyed in this land? And whereas those of the <hi>Hans,</hi> vented in <hi>Germany,</hi> only a matter of <hi>sixe thousand</hi> of our Clothes yeerely and at low prises: and held this <hi>Realme</hi> as it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding vnto them for their ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177945:46"/> yea vpon some discontent for denying of them priuiledges, durst offer some hostilitie in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Merchants-Aduenturers</hi> by their <hi>Charters,</hi> granted from time to time by the <hi>Princes of this Realme,</hi> and fauoured by <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> successiuely; by their order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mannaging of their trade, haue supplanted the trade of the <hi>Hanses</hi> in <hi>Germany:</hi> and brought the said <hi>Sixe thousand</hi> vented by them in <hi>Germany,</hi> vnto <hi>Thirtie thousand</hi> Clothes yeerely &amp; at great prises. And it is worthy to be remēbred to their <hi>Honour,</hi> that seruice which the <hi>Merchants-Aduenturers</hi> did to the <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 88. when they supplied the <hi>Nauie Royall</hi> with a whole ships lading of <hi>Powder and Shot</hi> from <hi>Hamburgh:</hi> which came luckily euen <hi>in articulo temporis,</hi> when there was a very great want thereof. These also haue from
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177945:47"/> time to time employed and bred vp many worthy Masters of ships and Mariners: and built many Tall, warlike and Seruiceable shippes: which as they themselues also, are at all times ready to doe seruice to the KING &amp; STATE vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. None of all which they had euer beene able to haue done as particular men, in a loose, distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and disorderly trade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The East-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</note>Great benefit also hath arisen from the <hi>East-land Company:</hi> who haue wonne like ground of the <hi>Hanses</hi> of the <hi>Baltique Sea:</hi> and do employ in that trade a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of proper <hi>Shippes</hi> and <hi>Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Muscouy Company</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Musco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy Company</note> also by the benefit of <hi>Gouernment,</hi> besides their imployment of many proper Ships and Men, haue discouered the passage by the <hi>North-Cape,</hi> as also of <hi>Greenland:</hi> and done many other seruices to the <hi>State:</hi> which as particuler men, they could neuer haue performed.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177945:47"/>
            <p>The <hi>Leuant Company</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Leuant Company.</note> likewise by their trade vnder <hi>Gouernment,</hi> hath built a great strength of warlike, Tall &amp; Lusty Shipping, which they employ in that trade: and by their industry haue wonne from the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> the trade of the <hi>Leuant:</hi> the <hi>Commodities</hi> whereof were before brought into this <hi>Realme</hi> by <hi>Argo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies</hi> to the encrease of <hi>Forreine ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> and at <hi>Deare</hi> rates: and is now reduced to the <hi>Natiues</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to the encrease of <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> and the benefit of the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</hi> Which without <hi>Gouernment</hi> and good order, had been impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to haue done.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French Company</hi>
               <note place="margin">The French Company.</note> also, though but lately reduced to <hi>Order,</hi> haue reformed many abuses in that trade, in maintaining the <hi>Natiue Commodities</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> in much better estimation, and in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the <hi>Forreine</hi> at moderate pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and in employing greater
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177945:48"/> shipping, then at any time before. Which were impossible for them to effect <hi>Singly,</hi> without <hi>Societie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, for the <hi>East-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The East-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</note> whereof I am preuented to say what I might, by two seuerall discourses published in print, the one by that worthy &amp; rarely qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Gentleman S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Dudley Digges</hi> Knight, the other by that discreete <hi>Merchant</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Mun:</hi> yet this I say, that this <hi>Great and Noble Societie</hi> by the benefite of <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> hath set on foot a very <hi>Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Trade,</hi> farre beyond any other <hi>Company</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome:</hi> and accordingly hath excelled in <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of shipping,</hi> and making <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners of land-men,</hi> beyond the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of any other Corporation: and had not <hi>Enuy</hi> thought that <hi>Trade</hi> too great a <hi>Treasure</hi> for this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> doubtlesse they had in <hi>Encrease of Trade,</hi> excelled all the <hi>Companies</hi> of <hi>Merchants</hi> in this <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:177945:48"/>
            <p>But here the ordinary obiection encountereth me, that in <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on answered, that the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countries trade without gouernment, which is exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by a particular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeration of diuers Countries.</note>
               <hi>Spaine, France, Italie,</hi> and the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> there are no such <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies,</hi> nor <hi>Restraint of Merchants,</hi> as here in <hi>England:</hi> and yet that those <hi>Countries</hi> thriue better in their Trades, then we in ours. I answer, that if it be granted, that they haue no such <hi>Companies</hi> nor <hi>Restraints</hi> of any, and that they thriue better in their trades then we; yet it will not follow, that this their better thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is because euery man is at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to be a <hi>Merchant</hi> at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. This is the <hi>Fallacy</hi> which the <hi>Logicians</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Non causa pro causa.</hi> For if that were the cause, why then should not our <hi>Spanish Trade,</hi> that hath no <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> nor <hi>Restraint,</hi> prosper better thē the other Trades which are <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Companies?</hi> whereas to speak as the truth is, <hi>This</hi> Trade &amp; <hi>These Merchants,</hi> are the most miserable
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177945:49"/> of all the other <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and all through want of <hi>Gouernment:</hi> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough whose sides the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> suffereth, and hath already lost many Millions in value of the <hi>Wealth</hi> of the <hi>Weale-publique,</hi> as I shall shew anon. But to the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption.</hi> I deny that the <hi>Merchāts</hi> of those <hi>Forreine Countries,</hi> trade without <hi>Gouernment.</hi> For <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> hath anciently had one <hi>Society,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As first Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</note> or <hi>Corporation</hi> of <hi>Merchants</hi> in all their <hi>Sea-townes,</hi> called the <hi>Society</hi> of the <hi>Hans,</hi> before noted: as their houses of <hi>Staple,</hi> yet standing at <hi>Bridges</hi> in <hi>Flanders, Antwerpe</hi> in <hi>Brabant, Nouogrode</hi> in <hi>Russia, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> in <hi>Norwaye,</hi> and the <hi>Steelyard</hi> in <hi>London</hi> can witnes. Which trade of theirs flourished, as long as it continued vnder <hi>Gouernment:</hi> but hauing lost their <hi>priuiledges,</hi> partly by their own <hi>Stragling,</hi> and partly being ouertop't by the flourishing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177945:49"/> of the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers Trade,</hi> their Trade is now almost quite fallen to the ground.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Portugall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spaine and Portugall.</note> all men know that their <hi>Sea Trade</hi> is little, sauing to the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West-Indies.</hi> And those Trades are carryed with <hi>Gouernement,</hi> and farre more restraint then ours.</p>
            <p>For <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">France.</note> there are not (that I know) any <hi>Companies</hi> of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> for forreine parts. Which I take to bee the cause, why those Merchants shipping, is of so small burthen, and of as little sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for seruice. Which is an effect of a stragling vngouerned Trade.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Italy.</note> that consisteth of so many seuerall <hi>Iurisdictions,</hi> that it were impossible to make a generall <hi>Corporation</hi> for any one kinde of <hi>Sea-trade.</hi> For example, were it not in vaine for <hi>Genoa</hi> to make a <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> &amp; <hi>Orders</hi> for Trade, whilest <hi>Florence</hi> held a contrary course? It
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177945:50"/> were certainly all one, as to haue a <hi>Company</hi> of Merchants for <hi>Spaine</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> and the <hi>West-parts</hi> left loose to Trade without <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Gouernment,</hi> which were a meere mockery. But the Trade in many parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> being carried by <hi>Families,</hi> and euery <hi>Family</hi> being as it were one Person, there is a kind of <hi>Gouernment</hi> in their Trades, and the same performed with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous credite, policie, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</note>The <hi>Low Countries,</hi> by that <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which is of the seuerall <hi>Townes and Prouinces</hi> vnder the <hi>States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> (which neuerthelesse is as much, and endureth as long, as euery seuerall <hi>Prouince and Towne</hi> listeth,) haue of late yeeres erected their <hi>East India Company,</hi> and the like for <hi>Guiny,</hi> and are in hand with the like for the <hi>West Indies.</hi> Also the <hi>Cloth-buyers,</hi> the principall <hi>Merchants of Holland,</hi> haue lately
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177945:50"/> obtained <hi>Octroy</hi> so termed, which is <hi>Priuiledges &amp; Immunities</hi> of the <hi>States,</hi> to assemble themselues, and to keepe Courts, and make Orders for their Trade; and principally to confront &amp; oppose the <hi>Merchants-Aduenturers</hi> Trade, vpon some differences, lately fallen out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt those <hi>Cloth-buyers</hi> and the said <hi>Company</hi> about the <hi>residence</hi> before noted. For their other Trades of <hi>Germany, Poland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wish then finde it possible, to ioine the seuerall <hi>Townes</hi> in one Rule and Order. And who so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerseth with that <hi>Nation,</hi> shall find that they very much complaine of the disorders of their Trades, for want of that kinde of <hi>Gouernment,</hi> which many of them take notice of here in <hi>England:</hi> and some of them of late haue desired instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from hence in that behalfe. Besides all this, these people as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:177945:51"/> they are borne and bred in an <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Country,</hi> so doth their nature and disposition encline much to an <hi>Vnion</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> in Trade. Insomuch as oftentimes they are able to worke their feates by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy</hi> and <hi>Combination,</hi> against an <hi>Incorporation</hi> in our <hi>Nation.</hi> For they wisely consider, that their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest is inuolued in the <hi>Publique:</hi> where, in our <hi>Nation,</hi> men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly preferre their <hi>Particular,</hi> to the <hi>Common-good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus hauing answered the obiections against <hi>Corporations,</hi> of <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Gouerned Trades,</hi> and shewed the many and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold benefits arising to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> thereby: It is now ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie to shew the Iniury and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience to this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> by the want of <hi>Gouernment in Trade.</hi> Those that Trade without <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Gouernment,</hi> are like vnto men, that make <hi>Holes</hi> in the bottome of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177945:51"/> that <hi>Ship,</hi> wherein themselues are <hi>Passengers.</hi> For want of <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in Trade, openeth a gap and letteth in all sorts of vnskilfull and disorderly persons: and these not only <hi>Sinke</hi> themselues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with them; but also <hi>Marre</hi> the Merchandize of the land, both in estimation and goodnesse: then which there can bee nothing in Trade more preiudiciall to the <hi>Publique Vtility.</hi> And to make good these particulers, I take this for a ground: <hi>Nemo nascitur artifex.</hi> Which as it is true in the occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Artizans:</hi> so is it much more true in the <hi>Trades</hi> of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants:</hi> wherein there is so great variety of difficult points to bee learned, before a man can learne his <hi>Stucke,</hi> as the Dutch-men speak, or be his <hi>Crafts master.</hi> And how can the <hi>Merchant,</hi> that hath no skill in his Commodity, looke to it, that the Maker performe his
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177945:52"/> part? Or how can a falsified Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, hold his estimation and vse? The ill experience whereof, is not more remarqueable in any of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> subiects, then in those that trade into the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> without <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Gouernment</hi> in Trade. For at the beginning of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> most happy Raigne ouer this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> this Trade by HIS <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Princely fauour,</hi> was made a <hi>Corporation</hi> and <hi>Societie</hi> of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi> and flourished vnder <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</hi> And then the new <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries,</hi> and other the <hi>Natiue Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> were maintained in their estimation and goodnesse at <hi>Home and Abroad:</hi> But soone after by the clamour of some who preferred their owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to the vtility of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and by some misinformation giuen the <hi>Parliament</hi> of that time, this <hi>Company</hi> after it had flourished
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177945:52"/> two yeares, was dissolued, and euer since exposed to confusion and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in Trade, and is become a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle and <hi>Rendes-vous</hi> for euery Shopkeeper, Stragler, and Vnskilful person: and may serue for a liuely representation of the hopes that may be expected, by such a loose trade, as many now a daies so much desire, not rightly conceiuing or considering the benefit of <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> nor the Inconueniencies that doe perpetually accompany trade in the want thereof. Which in the <hi>Effects</hi> will be more <hi>Perspicuous,</hi> to which in their Order we now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. V.</hi> Of the Effects of the former Causes as they concerne the <hi>KING.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SVCH were the <hi>Causes</hi> conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177945:53"/> trade. The <hi>Effects</hi> follow: which doe either concerne the KING, or the <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such as are the <hi>Causes,</hi> such also must needs be the <hi>Effects</hi> arising from the same: and those doe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther respect <hi>the</hi> KING in point of <hi>Honour,</hi> or in point <hi>of Reuenue:</hi> and both in the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> of Trade.</p>
            <p>In point of <hi>Honour,</hi> there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the KING from the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of Trade,<note place="margin">Effects to the King in point of Honour.</note> considered <hi>Generally,</hi> or <hi>Specially.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Generally,</hi> in the generall neglect of all trades, by remerous, rash, and litigious suites of law: whereby the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> is distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, the <hi>Iustice</hi> thereof abused, and in both the KING dishonoured.</p>
            <p>Or <hi>Specially</hi> in some speciall <hi>Commerce</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> abused by <hi>the</hi> KINGS Subiects, or Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. By <hi>the</hi> KINGS Subiects, in the <hi>Drapery</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> when
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:177945:53"/> HIS <hi>Maiesties Seale of Armes,</hi> which, as I said, is, <hi>Testis omni ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptione maior,</hi> shall be dishonoured by false Cloth and other Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, that are vnworthily honoured therewith: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, those that buy the same both <hi>within</hi> and <hi>without</hi> the Land, are perswaded the same is good and true, when the same is vtterly false: which is a great indignity offered to the KING.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Strangers,</hi> in the <hi>East India Action,</hi> and the matter of <hi>Fishing.</hi> In the <hi>East India Action</hi> certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the KINGS <hi>Honour</hi> is interessed; not onely to protect his subiects against the Iniuries done them by the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>East Indies;</hi> but also to maintaine the <hi>Glory and Renowne, of</hi> HIS <hi>Sacred Fame,</hi> which hath heretofore beene <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious</hi> euen vnto the <hi>Heathen:</hi> which some haue dared to doe what they could to obscure. The
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177945:54"/>
               <hi>Fishing</hi> hath also reference to <hi>the</hi> KINGS <hi>Honour:</hi> for it is a <hi>Royalty</hi> of the <hi>Crowne,</hi> which the KING in Honour cannot but protect.</p>
            <p>There is also an <hi>Effect</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth it selfe to the KINGS <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> in the <hi>Forme</hi> of Trade, as it is <hi>too strict,</hi> or <hi>too loose. Too strict,</hi> in respect of <hi>Monopolies,</hi> wherein the <hi>Prerogatiue of the</hi> KING is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused, and therein HIS <hi>Honour</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, by those that thereby seeke to priuiledge and Patronize things vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Too loose,</hi> in the disorderly Trade of the subiects out of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</hi> For those <hi>Strangers</hi> that haue not beene in our <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> nor seene the Order of HIS <hi>Maiesties Gouernment,</hi> must needes <hi>Ex vngue Leonem,</hi> guesse at the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne</hi> by the <hi>Subiect:</hi> And like to <hi>Archimedes</hi> who drew the whole pourtraiture of <hi>Hercules</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by his footstep onely found in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177945:54"/> Mount <hi>Olymphus,</hi> proportion the <hi>Royall and Regall Gouernment of</hi> HIS <hi>Maiestie At home,</hi> by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of his subiects <hi>Abroad.</hi> And as the Orderly Trade of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> is an <hi>Honour to the</hi> KING, when the same is contained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the listes of <hi>Gouernment;</hi> so the contrary cannot choose but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a quite contrary effect.</p>
            <p>In point of <hi>Reuenue</hi> the KINGS treasure is diminished,<note place="margin">In point of Reuenue.</note> in the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> also and <hi>Forme</hi> of Trade. In the <hi>Matter</hi> of Trade, eyther in the <hi>General</hi> course of Trade, or in some <hi>Particulers.</hi> In the <hi>Generall,</hi> the great want of money, and decay of Trade throughout all callings and conditions of men, must needes cause a great diminution of HIS <hi>Maiesties Reuenue,</hi> both in HIS <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes</hi> and <hi>Supplies.</hi> For the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes,</hi> those perpetually rise and fall with Trade: And for <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies,</hi> the subiects beeing impoueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177945:55"/> through want of Money and decay of Trade, are disabled to doe that seruice to HIS <hi>Maiesty,</hi> which otherwise they would be willing, and heretofore haue beene able to performe, in flourishing times of Trade. And if our experience here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of had beene in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and not in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the <hi>Contemplation</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not in <hi>Action:</hi> we had been much more happy in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>particuler</hi> course of Trade, it shall content me to instance one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>East India Action,</hi> and the <hi>Fishing,</hi> before referred to the KINGS <hi>Honour,</hi> here to HIS <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue.</hi> By the <hi>East India Action</hi> there is a very great losse to <hi>the</hi> KING in HIS <hi>Customes,</hi> by the losse of all the <hi>Custome</hi> which that Trade would haue produced in all this time: and of the <hi>Encrease</hi> also of <hi>Trade,</hi> which that employment had brought with it, which would
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:177945:55"/> haue yeelded to HIS <hi>Maiesty</hi> a great <hi>Increase</hi> of <hi>Customes</hi> answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the same. Of both which if we had not beene depriued, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely HIS <hi>Maiesties Ferme of</hi> HIS <hi>Customes</hi> had yeelded <hi>Many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds a yeare,</hi> more then now they haue done.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Fishing,</hi> the <hi>Customes and Tolles</hi> which are vndoubtedly due to HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> for the Strangers <hi>Fishing</hi> vpon our <hi>Coasts,</hi> together with the encrease of Trade, and consequently of <hi>Customes</hi> thereby also, wold amount to so great a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, that I cannot wonder enough, that the same hath beene neglected all this while.</p>
            <p>And lastly in the <hi>Forme</hi> of Trade, <hi>the</hi> KINGS <hi>Reuenue</hi> is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily diminished, when by the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of Trade, the very course of Trade is inuerted, and therein the KINGS <hi>Customes</hi> and <hi>Subsidies also.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:177945:56"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. VI.</hi> Of the Effects of the former Causes as they concerne the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</head>
            <p>FRom <hi>the</hi> KING, come to the <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Wherein there are also manifold <hi>Effects</hi> of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Causes,</hi> both in the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> of <hi>Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although in the very same things, wherein the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue</hi> of <hi>the</hi> KING are inuested, the <hi>Wealth</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is also interessed; yet the same may otherwise be distinguished, that so they may bee made the more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous and cleere to euery mans iudgement.<note place="margin">Effects to the Common-wealth Actiue and Passiue.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Effects</hi> then that arise out of the <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Trade</hi> and fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:177945:56"/> the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> may be saide to be either <hi>Actiue</hi> or <hi>Passiue. Actiue,</hi> when they are done by <hi>Our Selues: Passiue,</hi> when they are done to vs by <hi>others. Actiue,</hi> in the vse of <hi>Law,</hi> either <hi>Too much,</hi> or <hi>Too little. Too much,</hi> in <hi>Suits of Law,</hi> whereby one subiect vexeth another: which make this peaceable <hi>Kingdome</hi> seeme to be at Warre within it selfe. For whilest men are thus at <hi>Deadly Feude</hi> in Law, by the losse of their Times, and Trades, and States; the thrift of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> must needes bee neglected. <hi>Too little,</hi> In the <hi>Non-Execution</hi> of <hi>Lawes,</hi> which tend either to the enlargement of <hi>Clothing,</hi> or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint of the Excesse of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> The <hi>Former</hi> is, either in res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the <hi>Ill searching</hi> and <hi>Sealing</hi> of Cloth, or in the <hi>Transportation</hi> of the <hi>Materials</hi> of our Cloth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned. In the <hi>former</hi> of these, the <hi>Merchants Aduenturers</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:177945:57"/> can giue you an account of <hi>Tenne thousand pounds</hi> a yeare at least losse to this <hi>Commō-wealth,</hi> by the <hi>Tare</hi> or abatements vpon the Cloath in forreine parts, for the false making and sealing thereof: Besides the other <hi>Effects</hi> of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the <hi>Drapery</hi> it selfe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trades depending thereon, the losse whereof is vnualuable. In the <hi>Latter,</hi> euery man is sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the losse to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> in robbing it of the <hi>Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als:</hi> whereby not onely our <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries</hi> are <hi>Impaired,</hi> but the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine</hi> also are thereby much <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also the want of restraint of the <hi>Excesse</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> in <hi>Vsury</hi> and <hi>Prodigality:</hi> the one beeing a <hi>Viper</hi> in a <hi>Kingdome</hi> that gnaweth through the bowels thereof: the other a <hi>Canker</hi> that fretteth and wasteth the stocke, in spending the forreine wares, more then it ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177945:57"/> of our owne: both and either doe produce intollerable effects in a wel ordered <hi>Kingdome</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
            <p>Or <hi>Passiue,</hi> in the ill <hi>Effects</hi> that fall vpon the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> in things done to vs by <hi>Others.</hi> And that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Friends</hi> or <hi>Foes. The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> is done by <hi>Imposition,</hi> or <hi>Vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</hi> By <hi>Imposition,</hi> in the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Aduenturers</hi> Trade in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> where there is lately taxed vpon a Pack Cloth 9. <hi>Gilders;</hi> vpon a long Cloth 18. <hi>Gilders,</hi> and vpon a fine Cloth 24. <hi>Gilders,</hi> which is 18. 36. and 48. shillings of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. And yet neuerthelesse they free their owne Countrey Cloth of all manner of charge; nay, they giue encouragement to the makers thereof by many <hi>Priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Immunities:</hi> whereby it is more then manifest that they do what in them lyeth, to <hi>Plant</hi> their owne <hi>Draperies,</hi> and to <hi>Supplant</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:177945:58"/> ours, to the infinite disaduantage of this <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Vsurpation,</hi> those Friends of ours, depriue vs of our <hi>East India Trade,</hi> and <hi>Fishing,</hi> which here againe occurre, and offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues for this purpose also. By <hi>the Former,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> hath not onely been dispossest all this while of so great a Stocke, as is that of the <hi>East India Company,</hi> but of the employment and encrease of Trade also, that thereby in all this time would haue accrewed vnto this <hi>Kingdome.</hi> And it is to be feared, that their policy is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to depriue the <hi>Company</hi> of their <hi>Stocke,</hi> but the <hi>Kingdome</hi> also of the <hi>Trade:</hi> which they thinke too great and glorious a <hi>Fortune</hi> for this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> to enioy, and the onely hope of their's. And hence it is that the <hi>Restitution</hi> is so hard to be had, because they think by detaining it, and spinning out
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177945:58"/> the time, they shall in time <hi>Weary</hi> and <hi>Weare</hi> vs out of that Trade: And so in the meane while, by <hi>Plowing</hi> vp those <hi>Indian Seas and Soyle</hi> with our <hi>Heifers,</hi> they may at last <hi>Reape</hi> all the <hi>Haruest,</hi> and possesse and dispossesse at their owne pleasure, to the wonderfull enriching of their <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and the impouerishing of <hi>our's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>the latter,</hi> to wit, their <hi>Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon our Coasts,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> looseth that which they gaine: which is merueilous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of <hi>Trade,</hi> of <hi>Shippes,</hi> and <hi>Marriners.</hi> Whereby their <hi>Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> is mightily <hi>Strengthened,</hi> their <hi>Marriners multiplyed,</hi> and their <hi>Trade</hi> encreased: Of all which this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued, and <hi>their's</hi> enriched.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Foes</hi> also this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is lamentably <hi>Passiue,</hi> in the <hi>Cruelty</hi> done by <hi>Turkish Pirats</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Ships,</hi> and <hi>Goods.</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:177945:59"/> The griefe is lamentable, the losse intollerable.</p>
            <p>Lastly, there are ill Effects that fal vpon the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> in the <hi>Forme of Trade:</hi> and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of <hi>Monopolies,</hi> or <hi>Vngouerned Trade.</hi> By <hi>the Former,</hi> this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> is depriued of that true liberty of Trade, which belongeth to all the subiects: when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of some few, is preferred to the publique good.</p>
            <p>By <hi>the Latter,</hi> which is most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marqueable in the Trade of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> subiects into the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Mediterrane</hi> Sea; the Trade of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> consisting in <hi>Bayes, Perpetuanoes, Kersies, Waxe, Tinne, Lead,</hi> and other the <hi>Natiue Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> is betrayed into the hands, both of those with whom we are in <hi>Amitie,</hi> and others that are with vs in <hi>Enmity.</hi> The one taketh aduantage of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merchant-like
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:177945:59"/> courses for lacke of <hi>Order:</hi> The other, of our Shippes sent foorth stragling for lacke of <hi>Fleets:</hi> and both through want of <hi>Gouernment in Trade.</hi> Whereby the <hi>Perpetuanoes</hi> and other <hi>new Draperies</hi> haue by little and little bin made worse and worse, so that now they are become quite out of vse, the <hi>Trade lost,</hi> the <hi>Traders ruinated,</hi> the <hi>Manufactures by other Nations supplied,</hi> the <hi>Nauigation hindered,</hi> by the losse of many <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men,</hi> and <hi>Seruiceable Shippes:</hi> In all which, the <hi>Decay of Trade</hi> is exceeding <hi>Great,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth's</hi> losse <hi>Infinite.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:177945:60"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. VII.</hi> Of the Remedy for all the former Causes of decay of Trade.</head>
            <p>HAuing shewed the many and manifold <hi>Causes</hi> of the decay of Trade in the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> thereof: It remaineth now to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the <hi>Remedy.</hi> Which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the precedent Method, I will apply vnto all the particulers in their order. Onely the <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> for the <hi>Effects,</hi> I shall present in the <hi>Causes:</hi> for the <hi>Causes</hi> being remoued, the <hi>Effects</hi> must needs cease, according to the common <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>Philosophy, Sublatâ cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sâ tollitur effectus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my former distribution I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered the <hi>Causes</hi> of the decay of Trade, in the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> thereof: and in the <hi>Matter</hi> I insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted on <hi>Money and Merchandize.</hi> The <hi>Causes</hi> of the want of money, I shewed some to be <hi>Immediat;</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:177945:60"/> some <hi>Mediat</hi> or remote. The <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat</hi> Causes, I noted to be such, as either hinder the <hi>Importation;</hi> or such as cause the <hi>Exportation;</hi> and both in the <hi>Vnder-valuation</hi> of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> Coine.<note place="margin">The Remedy of drawing money into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, must needs be the raising therof.</note> The <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> offer's it selfe, which is double. First, how it may be got: and next how it may be kept. <hi>The former</hi> may be done two wayes: By Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the KINGS Coine; and by making current <hi>Forreine Coines</hi> at equall value.<note place="margin">And by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king forreine Coines cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant at like value.</note> Wherin it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, that the more the <hi>Coynage</hi> is abated, the lesse the <hi>Coyne</hi> it selfe need to be raised. <hi>The latter,</hi> to wit, the keeping of <hi>Money</hi> within the land, may also be done 2. waies: By another maner of Execution of the Statute for Employments then heretofore: wherein there is some reason not to expresse my selfe as I might: And by HIS <hi>Maiesties Princely and Prudent Negotiation,</hi> with the <hi>Princes</hi> of our <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177945:61"/> Countries,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited <hi>Prouinces</hi> especially, to keepe a more constant course in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues of their Coines. Neither of which can be done by that <hi>Par</hi> of Exchange, which is now againe in agitation, and hath taken more then twenty yeeres to bring it to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Wherein, <hi>absit invidia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi> that I say, there is neither <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> nor <hi>Purity.</hi> For it is not the rate of Exchanges, but the value of monies, here lowe, elsewhere high, which cause their Exportation: nor doe the Exchanges, but the plenty or scarcity of monies cause their values. Or if I should grant that to be the cause which is not: yet it doth not follow, that because the Stranger, like enough, would be a deliuerer heere of money at a high rate, that therefore the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish must take it. And then the consequence will be ill: for if the rate be such as the <hi>Taker</hi> like not,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:177945:61"/> then the <hi>Deliuerer</hi> is yet more thrust vpon the exportation. But I leaue this Proiect to whom it is committed, with this, that his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion seemes to be <hi>eiusdem fari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,</hi> with another of the same, in his <hi>Canker of Englands Common-wealth,</hi> in these words:<note place="margin">Canker of Englands Common-wealth. p. 46. published in <hi>An.</hi> 1601.</note>
               <hi>And it were to be wished, that our Cloth were sold at so deare a rate, and according to the price of forreine Commodities, that thereby other nations would take vpon them to make our Clothes themselues: which might easily bee remedied, by selling our woolles the dearer, whereof they must make them.</hi> Which seemes to haue in it much more <hi>Dutch</hi> then <hi>English,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue this <hi>Kingdome</hi> of so Royall a Manufacture, whereby so many thousands of poore families, are maintained in the same: as if hee would cure one Canker with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, contrary to our <hi>Sauiours Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,</hi> that Satan cannot cast out
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177945:62"/> Satan. But I returne to mine owne <hi>Station:</hi> and therein to answer the obiections that doe occurre the raising of <hi>Money:</hi> which are wont to be principally, either the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall <hi>Raising</hi> of it, to follow the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> of forreine Coine; or else the ineuitable losse that thereby will fall, <hi>Generally</hi> vpon all men in the endearing of all things; and <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly</hi> vpon <hi>Landlords</hi> and <hi>Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> in their rents and contracts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons against raising of money, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered.</note>For the continuall <hi>Raising</hi> of the Coine, that will be needlesse, if the meanes be sufficient for executing the <hi>Statute</hi> for <hi>employments,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Money</hi> may be kept within the land when we haue it. And for the dearenesse of things, which the <hi>Raising</hi> of <hi>Money</hi> bringeth with it, that will be abundantly recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto all in the plenty of <hi>Money,</hi> and quickning of Trade in euery mans hand. And that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to all, when hee that buye's
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177945:62"/> deare shall sell deare, cannot bee said to be iniurious vnto any. And it is much better for the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to haue things deare with plenty of <hi>Money,</hi> whereby men may liue in their seuerall callings: then to haue things cheape with want of <hi>Money,</hi> which now makes euery man complaine.</p>
            <p>Lastly, for <hi>Landlords and Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> their losse is easie to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by <hi>Prouiso,</hi> that the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts</hi> made before the raising of the <hi>Monies</hi> shall be paide at the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the <hi>Money</hi> went at, when the <hi>Contracts</hi> were made: according to the disposition of the <hi>Ciuill Law</hi> in this case:<note place="margin">Gailius <hi>2.</hi> lib. Obseruat. cap. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Valor monetae consideran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus &amp; inspiciendus est à tempore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus, non autem à tempore solutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The raising also of the <hi>Coine,</hi> would raise the price of <hi>Plate:</hi> whereby either there would bee lesse superfluity that way, or else
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177945:63"/> more old <hi>Plate,</hi> which perhaps in some mens hands is kept vp for <hi>Treasure,</hi> would be brought out, to be molten into <hi>Coine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Mediate</hi> or Remote <hi>Causes</hi> of the want of <hi>Money,</hi> I obserued to bee either <hi>Domestique or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine.</hi> The <hi>Domestique, Generall or Speciall.</hi> The <hi>Generall,</hi> the great <hi>Excesse</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> in consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Commodities of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Countries in such abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, to our owne losse. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst those, the great excesse in <hi>Tobacco</hi> is none of the least: which if it might seeme good to the High Wisedome of HIS <hi>Maiestie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Remedy for excesse.</note> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine, or at least to giue a tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>Barmudo's</hi> only: there might be a great deale of <hi>Pietie</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> shewed in this <hi>Remedy.</hi> For in the one respect, it would tend to a great enriching of that plantation, which so happily succeedeth through Gods blessing:
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177945:63"/> and in the other it would aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the KING and the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> in the redresse of the disorder of the <hi>Spanish Trade,</hi> and in bringing in <hi>Treasure</hi> in stead of that <hi>Toye,</hi> more then the Rent that is now rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> for the same,</p>
            <p>The Superfluity of other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities may bee restrained by lawes <hi>Vestiary</hi> and <hi>Sumptuary,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of <hi>Germany</hi> &amp; other our Neighbor Countries.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Speciall Remote Cause</hi> of our want of <hi>Money,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Remedy for want of Money in the remote cause thereof.</note> I noted to bee the want of our <hi>East India Stocke</hi> in the <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> The <hi>Remedy</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is in the <hi>Princely Power and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fauour</hi> of HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> to apply at HIS pleasure, to this Languishing body. And if HIS <hi>Sacred Maiestie</hi> will vouchsafe to apply HIS Gratious <hi>Mouth,</hi> to <hi>this Mouth:</hi> HIS waking <hi>Eye,</hi> to <hi>this Eye:</hi> HIS powerfull <hi>Hand</hi> to <hi>this Hand:</hi> then surely this fainted
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:177945:64"/>
               <hi>Body</hi> will receiue <hi>Breath</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> from the powerfull influence of so <hi>Great a Maiestie,</hi> and reuiue also the many other <hi>fainting</hi> Trades, that are <hi>fallen</hi> in it. The <hi>Forreine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Causes,</hi> I obserued to be the <hi>Warres in Christendome,</hi> or the <hi>Trades</hi> maintained with ready <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Out of Christendome.</hi> The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, either cause the <hi>Exportation</hi> of <hi>Money,</hi> as do the <hi>Warres</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians:</hi> or hinder the <hi>Importation</hi> thereof, as doe the <hi>Warres</hi> of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats.</hi> A <hi>Remedy</hi> in the former of these I know none,<note place="margin">A Remedy of the Warres of Christians.</note> besides that blessed disposition in HIS <hi>Maiesty</hi> to spare no <hi>Cost</hi> to make <hi>Peace:</hi> which hath made HIS <hi>Fame</hi> shine as farre as the Sunne shineth, and shall last as long as the Sunne and Moone endureth: and as sure as the Lord is faithfull, will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred on HIS <hi>Posterity</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: Besides this I say, I know none, but <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Prayer:</hi> that <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:177945:64"/> would auert the heauy Iudgments at this day on the Christian world, and giue vs grace to consider <hi>Our peace,</hi> in this <hi>Our day</hi> thereof. A <hi>Remedy</hi> in the latter,<note place="margin">A Remedy of disorderly Trade.</note> may be either by reducing of the stragling trade of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> subiects into the Dominions of the <hi>King of Spaine,</hi> into <hi>Gouernment;</hi> whereby they also might goe in Fleetes, as other gouerned Companies doe, and the better defend themselues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst so <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Cruel</hi> an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: or else by seeking restitution of our wrongs in this kinde, where it may be had: so farre as it may concurre with the <hi>Honour</hi> of the KING, to whose Great and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces iudgement, I submit the same.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Remedy</hi> for the <hi>Exportation of Money</hi> out of <hi>Christendome</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Remedy for the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portation of Money out of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> by the Trades before mentioned, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth much on the good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion hoped for, betweene the <hi>Dutch</hi> and our <hi>Nation.</hi> Whereby
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177945:65"/> not only the <hi>Indian Commodities,</hi> which in those Trades are the principall, may be bought much better cheape, and consequently spare a great deale of the <hi>Treasure</hi> now issued out for the same: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, the <hi>Natiue Commodities</hi> of either Country, and as much as may bee of euery Country, may be brought into <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Traine</hi> with the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> and aduanced in their vse and price: that so at last in stead of Money for Wares, we may giue Wares for Wares according to the Law and nature of <hi>Commerce.</hi> And this good conclusion betweene the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Vs,</hi> is the rather to bee wished, and the more to be haste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, because the subtilty of the <hi>Indians</hi> is great, in taking aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this vnhappy <hi>Faction,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fraction,</hi> that is fallen betwixt vs. For those that haue trauelled the <hi>Indies,</hi> and obserued those peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can tell, that the <hi>Indians</hi> doe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:177945:65"/> ascribe so much to the light of their vnderstanding, that they doe account the rest of the world blinde in Comparison of them. Only they vouchsafe to the people of <hi>Europe</hi> this honour, to call them <hi>One Eied men.</hi> Which also <hi>Maffei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> taketh notice of, in his History of the <hi>Indies,</hi> that those people dare beyond modesty thus to brag; <hi>Chinenses duos habere oculos;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. Petr. Maffeius Hist. Ind. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropaeos vnum; &amp; quod hominum est reliquum, caecutire. That the Chineses haue two Eies, the Europi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans one, and all the rest of the people of the world are blinde.</hi> And indeed they doe approoue themselues to be <hi>Quicke-sighted</hi> enough: for they are the <hi>Antipodes</hi> of <hi>Christians,</hi> and are in scituation farthest remote from them, and yet can finde the <hi>Meanes,</hi> to pry into the <hi>Mines</hi> and <hi>Treasure</hi> of the Christian world. And therefore I say, it is high time that the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>We</hi> left <hi>Darting</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:177945:66"/> at one another, and so ioine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that as with one <hi>Hand,</hi> and one <hi>Heart,</hi> and if they will needs haue it so, <hi>with that</hi> one <hi>Eie,</hi> we may collect and contract our shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest sence &amp; sight into it; that as it is said, some <hi>Monoculists,</hi> by the sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the sence drawne to one Eie, see better with that, then both: we may at last put this reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in practise, that we seem no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger blind men, to those <hi>Indian</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But herein on both parts, are we humbly to implore HIS <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Regall Intercession,</hi> that these differences, betwixt the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Vs,</hi> may no longer <hi>Hang in sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,</hi> but at last be drawne to that happy and hopefull <hi>Period</hi> wee haue so long looked &amp; longed for. That so the <hi>Maiesty</hi> of the KING, arising like the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Sun-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng</hi> vpon this our <hi>Horizon,</hi> may <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell</hi> and <hi>disperse</hi> all the tempestuous <hi>Mists</hi> and <hi>Fogges,</hi> that haue obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:177945:66"/> the same; and lend such a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> vnto this <hi>Orbe</hi> of ours, that <hi>They</hi> &amp; <hi>We,</hi> like louers and friends fallen at oddes, may be redintegrated, renewed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnited, in vnfaigned <hi>Amitie</hi> and <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> that the name of <hi>Hostilitie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Them</hi> and <hi>Vs,</hi> be neuer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after told in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publish't in the streets of <hi>Ashcalon:</hi> And that the Publike complaints aswell of their<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In a Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation out of a</hi> Dutch <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished in</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>by the</hi> Dutch <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: in the face or Title whereof, these words are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed:</hi> That notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme wrongs done by the <hi>MAIORS</hi> to the English Nation, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the East Indies; yet it is the Iustice of God, they thriue not with it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. <hi>Printed 26.</hi> Iune. <hi>1622.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Owne</hi> people, as <hi>Ours,</hi> may no longer come vnder the view and censure of the world.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Remedy</hi> of this kinde, may bee HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> gratious protection of the <hi>Persian Trade</hi> now so happily set on foote: that so neither the Enuy of any at Home; nor the <hi>Power or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy</hi> of any abroad, supplant vs in the same.<note place="margin">Another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of the former kinde.</note> Whereby the <hi>Cloth</hi> and <hi>Tinne,</hi> and other the <hi>Natiue Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> may be brought into <hi>Vse</hi> and <hi>Commerce</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:177945:67"/> the <hi>Persians</hi> also. Which through Gods blessing, and his <hi>Maiesties Royall Assistance,</hi> may be a means to draw the whole Trade of the <hi>Persian</hi> silke into this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and make it the <hi>Magazin</hi> thereof, for the supply of other Nations: to the weakning of the <hi>Turkes</hi> power, the increase of Trade in this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> and with it HIS <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</hi> Customes, the Nauigation, and employment of the poore: to the Great Honour of the KING, and enriching of all HIS <hi>Kingdomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so much for the <hi>Remedies</hi> about the <hi>matter</hi> of Trade in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> the <hi>Merchandize</hi> followeth. Which I considered <hi>Iointly,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</hi> The things that hindred the whole Trade, I noted to be <hi>Defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> as the <hi>want of Money,</hi> or the <hi>East India Stocke,</hi> which haue their <hi>Remedy</hi> before: or <hi>Efficient,</hi> as <hi>Vsury</hi> and <hi>Litigious Suits of law,</hi> to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies</hi> whereof we now proceede.<note place="margin">A Remedy for Vsury.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Remedy</hi> for <hi>Vsury,</hi> may be
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:177945:67"/> plenty of <hi>Money.</hi> For then, men will haue no such cause to take <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> at interest, as when <hi>Money</hi> is scant. For as it is the scarcitie of <hi>Money</hi> that maketh the high rates of interest: so the plentie of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> will make the rates low, better then any Statute for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. For although in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> it is lawfull for a man to take twenty in the hundred if he can get it: (wherein it seemes the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Tract against Vsury was misinformed,) yet there, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly money is let at 6. and 7. in the hundred, by reason of the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Money.</p>
            <p>Or there is another Remedy for Vsury,<note place="margin">Another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury.</note> in giuing liberty to the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, if so it may seeme good to HIS <hi>Maiesties High Wisedome,</hi> to buy and sell, and to transport Billes of debt from man to man: according to the Custome of <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> Which is found
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177945:68"/> to be an excellent meanes to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply mens wants in course of trade; and tendeth also to the enlarging thereof. And for the <hi>Extorsion</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the poore aboue noted: if a stocke of Money were raised in manner of a <hi>Lumbard,</hi> or otherwise in <hi>London,</hi> and in the <hi>Countries</hi> where much poore depend on Clothing, and else-where where there is cause, whereby the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of poore wherewith the <hi>Kingdom</hi> swarmeth, might be from time to time supplied for a small consideration; it would certainly giue great encouragement to the poore to labour, it would set on worke many fatherlesse children that are ready to sterue, it would benefit the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> by their labours, and it would be an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table worke to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> so to supply their wants, and not to suffer the faces of the poore to be ground by the extorsion of any.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:177945:68"/> And I am perswaded, that euery good man would be willing, either to giue, or to lend, toward the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of a stocke of <hi>Money</hi> for this purpose.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Litigious suits of Law,</hi> if men bestowed halfe that study and cost in trade, which now adaies is spent in temerous and rash suits of Law; surely the benefite that thence would arise to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> would equall or exceede in value, that which is spent in Law, which I thinke cannot be valued. The <hi>Remedy</hi> requireth great considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for such is the Cause.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>suites of Law</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome</hi> are now infinitely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creast,<note place="margin">Remedies for ligitious suits of Law.</note> to that they were in elder times, I thinke it is out of question: The <hi>Quaere</hi> is about the cause thereof. <hi>Litigious suits of Law,</hi> may seeme anciently to haue beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained, either by <hi>Sureties,</hi> or <hi>Fines,</hi> or both. <hi>Of the Former</hi> there is
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:177945:69"/> yet a defaced print in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mom-Pledges of <hi>Doe and Roe.</hi> Which were of old the names of true and reall sureties, but are now become formall only, and faigned names of Course and Solemnity. Whence also it is, that in stead of Reall sureties in <hi>London,</hi> faigned sureties are deuised from the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the party <hi>Plaintife:</hi> As for example: if the plaintife dwell in <hi>Cheape-side:</hi> they enter for his Sureties vpon the Record of Court, <hi>Iohn Cheape,</hi> and <hi>Richard Side.</hi> And in like manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer else the <hi>Plaintife</hi> dwelleth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the Latter,</hi> to wit of <hi>Fines,</hi> the vse of them both in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> &amp; <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> continueth vnto this day. <hi>In the Kings Bench</hi> the <hi>Fines</hi> are not so ancient, for those began in the 8. yeare of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> Happy raigne ouer this <hi>Kingdome:</hi> neither are they of like value to those of the <hi>Common-Pleas.</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:177945:69"/> Whereof HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> made then a <hi>Graunt</hi> to certaine <hi>Patentees</hi> for terme of yeares. But in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas,</hi> the <hi>Fines</hi> vpon <hi>Originall-Writs,</hi> are held by the learned in the Law, to bee as ancient as the <hi>Common-Law</hi> it selfe.</p>
            <p>Now whether the vse of <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> or the Institution of <hi>Fines,</hi> were inuented for the restraint of <hi>Ligitious suits of Law:</hi> or the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use and inequality of them, tendeth to the encrease thereof; I humbly leaue that, to the wisedome and iudgement of the <hi>Reuerend Iudges,</hi> and others learned in the Law: least I seeme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Neuerthelesse there seemes to me, to be a print of them, in the Lawes and Customes of <hi>Forreine Nations.</hi> For which, if you please, let vs heare MAIMON a great RABBI. HEBRAEI,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Maimon. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>litigiosum hominum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> saith he, <hi>duplum rependere coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerunt, qui debitum scienter denega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:177945:70"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bodin. de Rep. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>Also FESTVS POMPEIVS, cited by BODIN. <hi>Romani decimam partem eius rei, quae in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersiam veniret in priuatis, aut qui tam in publicis iudicijs, impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant. Ac licet Romani in Republica libera, Vectigalia &amp; tributa impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re sibi difficilimè paterentur, Vecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galia tamen Iudiciaria patienter tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In Part. iuris. De Actionib.</note>Also HOTTOMAN. <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Sacramentum constituerunt, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam viz. pecuniae summam, vt qui iudicio vicisset, suum sacramentū au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferret, victi autē ad aerarium rediret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De Rep. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>And lastly BODIN. <hi>Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus nonus Vectigal Iudiciarium ad cohibendam litigatorum hominum indomitam atque effraenatam licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam imperauit. Quo vix vllum af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictis aerarij opibus vtilius, &amp; Galliae Imperio litium innumerabili multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine oppresso, splendidius cogitari poterat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is also in <hi>France</hi> an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:177945:70"/> restraint of Law suits, by a <hi>Law Merchant,</hi> established in <hi>Roan, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Tholosa:</hi> whereby the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther higher Courts of Iustice are eased of those Knotty questions that often fall out in matters of <hi>Commerce,</hi> which are harder to bee determined by the learned in the Law, and not so hard for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and men of Trade.</p>
            <p>Like to which, is that of the <hi>Court of Conscience,</hi> and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for <hi>Pollicies of Assurance</hi> in London. The one granted by an Act of Parliament, in the 3. yeare of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> happy Raigne, the other by the Statute of 43. <hi>Eliz.</hi> And both are executed by <hi>Merchants</hi> and men of Trade: though in the latter the Statute ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth certaine Ciuill and Common Lawyers with them in Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to assist them when there is cause: because such Assurances are grounded on the Ciuill Law. By
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:177945:71"/> which meanes HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> other Courts of Iustice are eased of the multiplicitie of Questions that might arise by suits of Law of this kinde.</p>
            <p>And thus hauing been bold to make this short Relation of my poore obseruation herein, I most humbly submit this <hi>Remedy</hi> to the High wisedome of HIS <hi>Maiestie,</hi> to dispose thereof in such Manner and Measure, as the Nature and Number of the suits of Law, at this day in this Kingdome doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. In the restraint whereof, HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> shall haue great <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour:</hi> HIS <hi>Kingdome Peace:</hi> the <hi>Iudges Ease:</hi> the <hi>Subiects Quietnesse,</hi> and the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> increase of <hi>Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Remedies for Ordinance.</note>The Trades considered <hi>Apart,</hi> I reduced to such, as tend to the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of the Kingdome,</hi> or <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Trade.</hi> The former I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be <hi>Ordinance</hi> or <hi>Munition.</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:177945:71"/> In which case the <hi>Philosopher</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth good Counsell,<note place="margin">Bias:</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sic aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tanquam sis osurus, sic oportet odisse tanquam sis amaturus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter I reduced to <hi>Fishing</hi> and <hi>Clothing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing.</note> as the <hi>Nurseries</hi> of Trade. For the <hi>Fishing,</hi> the infinite treasure that Strangers search out of our Seas, the variety of Trade that thereby they purchase, the multitude of <hi>Mariners</hi> they breed, the Fleets of Shipping they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,<note place="margin">Quae non pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunt singula, multa invant, De remed.</note> me thinkes should euery of them apart, or all of them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be vnto vs as so many prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to rouze vs vp to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise thereof: Whereby HIS <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie</hi> might receiue such a Tolle or Custome of them, as other Princes doe in like case, and be once againe <hi>Lord and Master</hi> of the Seas, for all the dispute of the Author of <hi>Mare liberum:</hi> and the Natiue subiect en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by some Immunity or
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:177945:72"/> Priuiledge, to lay hold on that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, which God and Nature hath brought home to our doores.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Clothing,</hi> that also is a point of <hi>State</hi> and <hi>great conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</hi> The <hi>Causes</hi> of the decay whereof, I obserued to bee either <hi>Domestique</hi> or <hi>Forreine.</hi> The <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestique</hi> some <hi>Past,</hi> some <hi>Present.</hi> In which former, it may perhaps seeme strange, to speake of a <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> for a thing past. Wherein the best Remedy I can thinke of, is, to be warned by those harmes, not to disturbe or distract Trade vpon any suggestion, though neuer so specious. It is a safe rule, that in <hi>Rebus nouis constituendis euidens esse debet vtilitas.</hi> And in <hi>Proiects,</hi> though they promise much, yet the vtility is commonly <hi>Contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,</hi> which may be, or may not be. But in the mutation of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall course of Trade, there ought to be <hi>Perspicuity</hi> and <hi>Apparency</hi> of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:177945:72"/>
               <hi>Euident Vtility:</hi> Else a <hi>Breach</hi> may be sooner made in Trade then can be <hi>repaired:</hi> and the <hi>Current</hi> once <hi>diuerted,</hi> will hardly bee <hi>reuolued,</hi> into it genuine <hi>Source</hi> and <hi>Course</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>present Domestique Causes</hi> of the Decay of <hi>Clothing,</hi> I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the Trade vnder the <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier,</hi> or vnder the <hi>Merchant.</hi> Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Clothier,</hi> I noted the <hi>Ill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> and <hi>False sealing</hi> of Cloth: and both through the <hi>Non-executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Statute of 4. of the KING. The abuse wherof is growne to be very great, and the reformation hath beene by HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations and otherwise, so much and so oft attempted of late yeares, and nothing therein effected, that it seemeth a very difficult matter to reforme the same. Neuerthelesse if it may please HIS <hi>Maiestie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Remedy for Clothing.</note> to commit the care of the execution of the Statute, to some of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:177945:73"/> Cities and Townes in the Clothing Counties,<note place="margin">The Remedy for Clothing.</note> where Broad Clothes, Kersies, and Perpetuanoes are made; and to make them the <hi>Ouerseers</hi> mentioned in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, instead of those ignorant and negligent <hi>Searchers,</hi> with reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble allowance for their paines; I am confident it would proue a singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Remedy. For we haue not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the example of the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Examples of <hi>Worcester, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </note> where this course is taken, but also here with vs: as <hi>Worcester</hi> for that sort of Clothes, <hi>Colchester</hi> for Bayes, and <hi>Canterbury</hi> for Sayes. In all which places the former abuses are remoued by this means; and the Clothes, and Bayes, and Manufactures of those Cities, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in great credit and estimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Which execution of the saide Statute, is the rather to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the care and charge of the principall Cities and Townes in the Clothing Counties; because
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:177945:73"/> by ancient Statutes not repealed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> &amp;, <hi>5.</hi> P. &amp; M. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> all Clothes and Kersies ought to bee brought to the next City, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, or Towne Corporate, to be sealed, before they be put to sale. And if such Clothes so sealed, proue defectiue, that Corporation or Towneship that so hath sealed them, shall forfeit the whole value thereof.</p>
            <p>The reformation of which abuse will redound to the benefit of the <hi>Clothier,</hi> as well as the <hi>Merchant.</hi> For none is more hurt with false Cloth, then that Clothier which maketh true Cloth: because his markets are alwayes hurt by the cheapnesse that false Cloth may be afforded at. Therefore to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate this Remedy, I haue made a collection of all the principall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Townes in the Clothing Counties for this purpose, as by a list thereof, fixed to the end of this discourse may appeare, that so a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:177945:74"/> worke of this nature be no longer deferred, wherein the <hi>Honour of the</hi> KING, and the <hi>Benefit</hi> of the <hi>Publique</hi> are so much inuolued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Remedy for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Wools.</note>Vnder the <hi>Merchant</hi> I obserued the Cloth-Trade to suffer at <hi>Home</hi> and <hi>Abroad:</hi> At <hi>Home,</hi> either by exporting the <hi>Materials</hi> of Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or by Ore-lading the Cloth-Trade with charge. The Remedy in the former, were to lay a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint of exportation of Wools and Wool-fels out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to quicken the execution of the Statute for that purpose in <hi>England,</hi> by encouraging the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerers of such abuses.</p>
            <p>The latter is the Sur-charging of the Cloth Trade, either generally or specially: this last, in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions and Imprest monies im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by the <hi>Merchant Aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers:</hi> which as it is a charge laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Drapery</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> I conceiue, vnder fauour, is a matter
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:177945:74"/> that trencheth into the Supreme power and dignity of the KING, and is peculiar to HIM alone. And if for <hi>Gouernment,</hi> or other iust cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in <hi>Societies</hi> and <hi>Corporations,</hi> there be a necessity of paying of debts, or defraying of necessary charge;<note place="margin">A Remedy for the charge vpon the Cloth.</note> I should thinke it better policy to spare the <hi>Cloth,</hi> and other the <hi>Natiue Commodities</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and to implore HIS <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties</hi> fauour, to leuy such charge vpon the <hi>Forreine Commodities:</hi> according to the Counsell of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stephan lib. Senten.</note>
               <hi>Si Vectigal nouum euitari non potest, tunc onerentur merces pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigrinae, quae ad luxum magis quàm ad necessitatem faciunt.</hi> And this I conceiue would be a good reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for easing the Cloth Trade of the present charge vnder the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants: which would also bee a meanes for paying of their debts, with a little more length of time, and a great deale of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:177945:75"/> both to Clothiers and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in the Cloth Trade.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Abroad,</hi> if it appeare vpon examination, that the Residence of the Merchant Aduenturers at <hi>Delft</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> be inconuenient for the Trade: As HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> was graciously pleased to giue them that liberty for a tryall, so it may please HIS <hi>Maiestie</hi> to dispose thereof, in some more fit place for their's and the <hi>Publique good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Forreine Causes</hi> of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the <hi>Drapery,</hi> I noted to bee <hi>Generall,</hi> as the <hi>Warres;</hi> or <hi>Speciall,</hi> as the great <hi>Imposition in Holland.</hi> The one is the worke of <hi>God,</hi> the other of the KING, to remoue the same. To whom I recommend them both.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Remedy for Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and too strict Trade.</note>And thus farre for the <hi>Remedies</hi> in the <hi>Matter of Trade,</hi> considered in <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Merchandize:</hi> the <hi>Forme</hi> followeth in <hi>Gouerned</hi> and <hi>Vngouerned Trade.</hi> In the <hi>Former</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:177945:75"/> I obserued a <hi>too strict,</hi> and in the <hi>latter</hi> a <hi>too loose</hi> forme of Trade. The <hi>Remedy</hi> in the One, if it seeme good to the high wisedome of HIS <hi>Maiestie,</hi> may be <hi>Priuatiue,</hi> in racing and rooting out the name and vse of <hi>Monopolies</hi> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst this Nation, as HIS <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie</hi> hath royally begun in that HIS Gracious Proclamation before mentioned. And to free and open the course of Trade, where now it is vnequally stopt, to the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the subiects, and the benefit of the Publique.</p>
            <p>In the other <hi>Positiue,</hi> by dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the Trades of HIS <hi>Maiesties</hi> subiects that are now distracted; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Gouernment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Remedy for too loose Trade.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of none hath more need, as hath been shewed, then those that Trade into the Dominions of the <hi>King of Spaine.</hi> Whose Trade the rather calleth for redresse, because it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth Cloth and other the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:177945:76"/> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and importeth <hi>Treasure,</hi> the life of Trade: In both which there is now a marueilous great defect, and Trade in all mens hands <hi>become so poore and leane,</hi> that it doth scarce, <hi>haerere ossibus.</hi> For where <hi>Trade</hi> is <hi>disordred,</hi> and the <hi>Traders vngouerned,</hi> there they are like a house deuided, which cannot long subsist: according to that of the Orator,<note place="margin">Cic. de Legib.</note>
               <hi>Nec domus vlla, nec Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas, nec Societas, nec Gens, nec ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum vniuersum genus stare, nec rerum natura omnis, nec sine imperio mundus ipse potest.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_towns">
            <pb facs="tcp:177945:76"/>
            <list>
               <item>The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Townes, for execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Statute for searching and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Cloth, are in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<list>
                     <item>Three grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<list>
                           <item>Wiltshire
<list>
                                 <item>Salisbury. Wilton.</item>
                                 <item>Westbury. Trubrigde.</item>
                                 <item>Wotton-Baslet. Deuizes.</item>
                                 <item>Malmsbury. Chipnam.</item>
                                 <item>Castlecomb. Calne.</item>
                                 <item>Bradford. Bromhil.</item>
                                 <item>Beckinton. Warminster.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Somersetsh.
<list>
                                 <item>Bath. Wells.</item>
                                 <item>Freshford. Taunton.</item>
                                 <item>Philips-Norton. Frome.</item>
                                 <item>Somerton. Wellington.</item>
                                 <item>Bridgewater. Ilmister.</item>
                                 <item>Axbridge. Glastonbury.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Glocestersh
<list>
                                 <item>Glocester. Tedbury.</item>
                                 <item>Strowdwater. Dursley.</item>
                                 <item>Wotten-vnderhedge.</item>
                                 <item>Ebley. Witcomb.</item>
                                 <item>Winchcomb. Thornbury</item>
                                 <item>Teuxbury. Cirencester.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sixe lesse
<list>
                           <item>Oxfordshire. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ford. Witney.</item>
                           <item>Worcesters. Worcester. Kidderminster</item>
                           <item>Herefordshire. Hereford. Lidbury.</item>
                           <item>Warwickshire. Warwicke. Couentry.</item>
                           <item>Deuonshire. Exceter. Tanton.</item>
                           <item>Hampsh. Southampton. Portsmouth.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>